<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true and exact relation of the great and heavy pressures and grievances the well-affected of the northern bordering countries lye under, by Sir Arthur Haslerigs misgovernment, and placing in authority there for justices of the peace, commissioners for the militia, ministry, and sequestrations, malignants, and men disaffected to the present government, set forth in the petition, articles, letters and remonstrance, humbly presented to the councel of state, with his apologie to the Lord President, for publishing thereof. / By John Musgrave.</title>
            <author>Musgrave, John, fl. 1654.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 130 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89428</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M3153</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E619_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206368</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865529</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865529</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117774</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89428)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117774)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 95:E619[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true and exact relation of the great and heavy pressures and grievances the well-affected of the northern bordering countries lye under, by Sir Arthur Haslerigs misgovernment, and placing in authority there for justices of the peace, commissioners for the militia, ministry, and sequestrations, malignants, and men disaffected to the present government, set forth in the petition, articles, letters and remonstrance, humbly presented to the councel of state, with his apologie to the Lord President, for publishing thereof. / By John Musgrave.</title>
                  <author>Musgrave, John, fl. 1654.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 9, [1], 7-49 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed Anno Dom. 1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Text continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb 14".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hesilrige, Arthur, --  Sir, d. 1661.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117774:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A true and exact RELATION Of the great and heavy PRESSURES AND GRIEVANCES THE Well-affected of the <hi>Northern</hi> bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Counties lye under, by Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerigs</hi> miſgovernment, and placing in Authority there for <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> of the <hi>Peace, Commiſſioners</hi> for the <hi>Militia, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry,</hi> and <hi>Sequeſtrations, Malignants,</hi> and <hi>Men</hi> diſ-affected to the preſent <hi>Government,</hi> ſet forth in the <hi>Petition, Articles, Letters</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance,</hi> humbly preſented to the <hi>Councel of State,</hi> with his <hi>Apologie</hi> to the <hi>Lord Preſident,</hi> for publiſhing thereof.</p>
            <p>By JOHN MUSGRAVE.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t jugulent homines Surgunt de nocte lationes:</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t teipſum ſerves, nonne expergiſceris?</l>
               <l>Latet anguis inſerba.</l>
               <l>Quod verum atque deceus curo et rego, et omius in hoc ſum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>London, Printed <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:117774:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117774:2"/>
            <head>The Apologie of <hi>John Musgrave,</hi> to the Right Honourable <hi>John Bradſham,</hi> for his publiſhing his Petition and Charges againſt S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>: <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge,</hi> and others put in Authority by him; with ſeveral Letters, and his <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance</hi> to the Councel of State.</head>
            <div type="apology">
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>KNowing my own weaknes and imbecillity, and the power and greatneſs of my oppoſites, if I had looked only upon out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward helps, I ſhould wholly have been deterred from enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the liſts with thoſe great ones, whom I have to deal with, and no doubt but of many of my friends, I ſhall be blamed, and of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as much or more envied for undertaking this quarrel, as <hi>David</hi> was of his <hi>Brethren,</hi> for leaving his Fathers Sheep and taking the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> challenge to fight with him, whom the whole Hoſt of <hi>Iſrael</hi> feared; and be accounted no leſs proud, and fooliſh, then <hi>Eliab</hi> did his Brother <hi>David;</hi> But when they ſhall behold this great <hi>Giant,</hi> and mighty <hi>Nimrod</hi> of the <hi>North,</hi> with his whole Hoſt and <hi>Militia,</hi> wherewith he is guarded, thrown down and broken without any other Armory, but by the ſtrength of truths diſcovery by me, one whom he ſo much diſeſteemes, and ſee him and them as ſuddenly fall, as the great <hi>Philiſtine</hi> did, when ſmitten with the ſtone caſt out of <hi>Davids</hi> ſling. My <hi>Countreymen</hi> will be then rather aſhamed of their faint-heartedneſs, to have ſat ſtill and bin only as idle ſpectators, while I for mine and their Countries liberty, did contend with theſe <hi>Cedars,</hi> and Sonnes of <hi>Anack.</hi> And though for ſundry years, while I have thus ſtrugled and contended, I have often found theſe Sonnes of <hi>Zervia</hi> too hard for me; yet when I was as a Man without hopes, ſeeing no way of eſcape, even then, God ſent me an unexpected delivery, which makes me more bold, and with leſſe carefulneſs, to wait upon the good hand of Gods provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117774:3"/>to carry me on in this buſineſs, whereon the welfare and ſafety of ſo many thouſands depends. I will not deny but in this very thing I have too much conſulted with fleſh and blood, and reſted more then I ſhould upon the rotten props of outward means; and by the deceitful blandiſhments of the adverſary, ſpeaking fair, and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing peace, I was almoſt taken in the <hi>Phyliſtines</hi> Trapp, and ready to be inchained up in their fetters, if by a ſudden Alarum of a new enemies approach, I had not been awaked out of my ſleep of ſecurity, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with I was very much overtaken; for after two years, hard and cruel impriſonment in the <hi>Fleet,</hi> (committed to that Priſon for no other cauſe, as your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> well knowes, then for the like diſcovery as this, &amp; proſecuting ſome powerful enemies, who then ſatt in the great Councel of this Nation, having under the falſe vizard of friends, got themſelves into the greateſt places of Authority and truſt in our parts; being reſtored to my liberty, upon the <hi>Lord Generals</hi> taking notice of my wrongful impriſonment, I was fully reſolved not further to have buſied my ſelf with matters of State, but wholly left the ſame to the care and ordering of thoſe that ſat at the ſterne, &amp; only applyed my ſelf to my home buſineſs, &amp; lived retired: but in this I was much deceived, for I was no ſooner retired to my Countrey, but I underſtood ſome men now in great favour, &amp; now highly promoted, and intruſted, by our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour and <hi>Sejanus</hi> of the <hi>North,</hi> were upon a Clandeſtine deſign, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be put in execution for bringing in the <hi>Scots</hi> to force the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and ſeize upon us before we ſhould miſtruſt, or be in any wiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to prevent the ſame; So, as of a ſudden being ſecure as we thought, we were ſurrounded with our enemies on every ſide, and had been without recovery, if by the valour and gallantry of the now victorious Gen. in the overthrow of the great Duke of <hi>Scotland,</hi> we had not been reſcued; and after taken under his <hi>Excellencies</hi> protection; and though the General ſtayed but a very little time amongſt us, (for he gave himſelf no reſt there, while the enemy had any ſtrength unbroken) yet by his preſence, and countenance for the time he was with us, we were much refreſhed; but the L.G. <hi>Cromwel</hi> withdrawing, we thence were left to the care and charge of Sir <hi>Arthur H.</hi> Governour of the bordering Counties and Gariſons, a man in whom we had great hopes, and had promiſed great matters, <hi>(ſed Magiſtratus inditat virum;)</hi> he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived our expectation, he takes for his Friends, favourites <hi>Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours,</hi> and boſome acquaintance, ſuch as were profeſſed enemies to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117774:3"/>this <hi>Commonwealth;</hi> and preferrs none other; he ſlights, derides, and keep under all the cordial, and well affected; and whom the now L. Gen had preferred, and owned, Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> with diſreſpect laies aſide, which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed me, conſtrained by neceſſity, (for no other with us would or durſt) unwillingly <hi>(durum telum neceſſitas)</hi> once again to put my ſelf forth by a <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> to the <hi>Councel of State;</hi> for (by no hand could I have acceſs to the <hi>Parliament</hi>) &amp; ſet forth the ſad and lamentable conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Countrey, and the great and heavy oppreſſions we lay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, by the diſorder and miſgovernment of thoſe placed in Authority, by Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerigs</hi> procurement, and recommendation, in which <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> I had that tender regard and reſpect to Sir <hi>Arthur H.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving him to be abuſed and deceived in this his complying with the malignant party, through their ſubtil inſinuations, (he being a ſtranger in that Countrey) as I did not ſo much as once mention his name in my <hi>Remonſtrance,</hi> though I had been many wayes provoked thereunto; I muſt ever with all thankfulneſs acknowledge your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips</hi> favour and benignity; for by your only means I muſt confeſs, I had acceſs unto, and audience before that Honourable <hi>Councel of State,</hi> (as I have had ſundry times ſince) who were pleaſed to take cognizance of my <hi>Remonſtrance,</hi> and upon reading the ſame, and hearing my ſelf made their <hi>Declaration,</hi> promiſing relief, and redreſs, as well of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, as of publick grievances therein complained of, but by other great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er buſineſs of State, hath bin hindered in the proceed thereof; ſo as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their intention, (as I believe) we have not had any fruit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. (My Lord) it is not to be believed what rejoycing this your <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> was to your <hi>Northern</hi> Friends, and how therewith their dying ſpirits were revived, as if they had bin already delivered from under the hand of their cruel <hi>Egyptian Taskmaſters,</hi> who exacted their ſtinted number of brick without allowance of any ſtraw, and hoped their bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage ſhould have ended in the firſt year of <hi>Englands</hi> Freedom, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las! their ſunne was ſoon overclouded, and an unexpected ſtorm of a ſudden doth ariſe, ready to over-whelm them in a Sea of new ttoubles; when their Ship was ready to arrive at the Haven of their wiſhed deſires. Mr. <hi>Howard,</hi> a moſt dangerous and notorious delinquent, in Arms againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> both in the firſt and ſecond War, a man of great wealth, and very powerful in his Countrey, who in the laſt War, raiſed great Forces, and muſtered 8000 men for the enemy, who at his <hi>Muſter</hi> declared for the late <hi>King,</hi> &amp; ſaid he was to meet the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117774:4"/>
                  <hi>Prince</hi> at <hi>Barwick,</hi> cauſing his Souldiers to ſhout, a <hi>King</hi> a <hi>King,</hi> in holding up their naked ſwords in his houſe, hath for his <hi>Councellour</hi> one Followfield a Lawyer, a dangerous <hi>Papiſt,</hi> being but the other day with the <hi>Rebels</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and for his <hi>Chaplain</hi> a <hi>Malignant-Prieſt,</hi> late <hi>Preacher</hi> to the <hi>King</hi> at <hi>Oxford,</hi> in his <hi>Gariſon</hi> there, I ſay that Mr. <hi>Howard,</hi> by whoſe recommendation I know not, if not by Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig,</hi> within two moneths that I had preſented my <hi>Remonſtrance,</hi> as aforeſaid, is made High Sheriff of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> to the lifting up the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant</hi> ſpirits; I complain to Sir <hi>Arthur H.</hi> of this, he ſlights it, or rather approves of it; few days after Sir <hi>Arthur H.</hi> as of purpoſe to ſet up the enemy with high hand, preſents to the <hi>Councel of State</hi> for <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> of the <hi>Militia</hi> for our <hi>Countrey, Mr. Howards</hi> Vaſſalls and Creatures, known <hi>Delinquents,</hi> and men profeſſedly enemies to the preſent <hi>Government;</hi> openly and liberally I ſpeak againſt Sir <hi>Arthur H.</hi> for ſo doing, he procures an <hi>Order,</hi> and convents me before the <hi>Councel of State,</hi> to give in my exceptions, and the reaſons of my exceptions to the men, thinking by his greatneſs and power, to have born me down; but after long debate upon my exceptions, he promiſed to the <hi>Councel of State</hi> to lay theſe men aſide, as unworthy, that truſt and imployment, pleads miſpriſion, and how he was abuſed by <hi>Thomas Crayſtor,</hi> Major of <hi>Carliſle,</hi> whoſe <hi>Letters</hi> for theſe men he ſhewed; but upon our Noble, and ever to be honoured Generals return from <hi>Ireland,</hi> and his march for <hi>Scotland,</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur H.</hi> procures the before excepted men to be <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> for our <hi>Militia,</hi> a boldneſs not to be paralleld, and a fault not excuſable, acting as if he were above Law, above the <hi>Parliament.</hi> After he returns into the <hi>Countrey</hi> to <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents our <hi>Miniſtry</hi> before him: the <hi>Engagement</hi> he mentions not, nay ſome are threatned with impriſonment, for deſiring the ſame to be ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to ſome <hi>Scottiſh Malignant Prieſts</hi> which are beneficed with us, he eſtabliſhes in the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> malignant, ſcandalous, and ſuch as be oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to the <hi>Engagement,</hi> our honeſt <hi>Miniſters</hi> and your friends he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenanceth, ſilenceth, and ſequeſters, putting in their places men diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected, and Mr. <hi>Nichols</hi> Sheriffe <hi>Howards</hi> Chaplain, whom before I ſpoke of upon the recommendation of <hi>Mr. Crayſtor,</hi> (as from a good hand is certefied me) ſince I came thence, he hath placed at <hi>Aicton;</hi> where before <hi>Mr. Lampit</hi> ſerved faithfully the cure. I pray your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> conſider, whether if your enemy in Armes were poſſeſſed of that Countrey, could do you this way more diſſervice and more injure
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117774:4"/>your friends; but why complain I alone? read theſe following <hi>Letters,</hi> am I not blamed for my long ſilence, as either conniving at, conſenting, or at leaſt concealing Sir <hi>Arthur H.</hi> exorbitancy and oppreſſions, therefore leaſt I ſhould prove guilty herein, of betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my own and Countries Liberty, I have, as <hi>Eſther</hi> did in the like caſe and extremity preſent her ſelf before the <hi>King,</hi> put all to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, and contrary to your Law and Order, come thus into your preſence, and rather then this grand impoſtor of State ſhould not be unmasked, I have caſt my ſelf upon your bounty, and if I periſh, I periſh, pardon my <hi>Lord</hi> this my preſumption, conſider our condition, and ſpeak peace unto us, we are brought to the like exigency, and ſtrait as the <hi>Lepers</hi> of <hi>Samaria;</hi> if we now hold our peace, we dye, and if we put our ſelves out, our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition cannot be worſe; nay, I had rather be in your priſon, then live as we do, under Sir <hi>Arthur H.</hi> in liberty, which very thing and no other, is the cauſe, that without an <hi>Imprimatur,</hi> I have thus publiſhed his illegal, irregular actings, his breach of faith and truſt, and what manner of men he imployes and intruſts, and how they order things, and behave themſelves in their publick Offices; but if any object and ſay, that I ſtrengthen the enemy by thus diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering breaches amongſt our ſelves. I anſwer, the enemy within the Rib of the <hi>Trojan</hi> Horſe in one night, burned that great City which the <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Greece</hi> in ten years Warre with all their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, could never enter; and is not Sir <hi>Arthur H.</hi> made Guardian and Keeper of your ſtrong Holds and Cities, bordering upon the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidious <hi>Scot,</hi> your unreconciliable enemy; and by the laying open the rottonneſs of theſe men, the enemy will be much fruſtrated of their hopes, and prevented in their deſign, when they cannot have a party among us longer undiſcovered, to uphold their intereſt by the Sword of Authority, and ſuch hereafter as we ſhall intruſt and imploy, when they know they cannot eſcape unpuniſhed, if they ſhould falſifie their truſt, will be more careful to diſcharge their duty: And ſuch have been <hi>Patriots</hi> of their <hi>Countrey,</hi> who have minded the good of the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> and not their own <hi>Wealth;</hi> as bleſſed be <hi>God</hi> for it, many there be placed in ſeveral ſeats of your higheſt <hi>Judicatures,</hi> will be incouraged to act with higher reſolutions without fear, for the Honour of the <hi>State</hi> there, the good and comfort of the People, and be to their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117774:5"/>own verlaſting praiſe. the cauſes of all the late tumultuous riſings &amp; inſurrections here, in <hi>Wales</hi> &amp; the <hi>North,</hi> were occaſioned by no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then ſome of your boſom enemies; ſuch have been the cauſe of theſe diſtractions, and the continuance of this War thus long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us; and till juſtice be done impartially, &amp; your corrupt <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> of <hi>State</hi> be brought to account, you can expect no end of theſe troubles. Slight us not herein, it concernes your peace, your ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; for if ſuch men as we complain of be kept in Authority by new diviſions through their miſgovernment, will indanger (if this Warre were ended, and all your enemies broken) to foment &amp; raiſe new troubles, greater and more dangerous combuſtions then any we have had, or yet undergon, <hi>premoniti premuniti:</hi> Therefore my <hi>Lord,</hi> you being ſo concerned, and your intereſt ſo great, and your welfare ſo much depending upon the <hi>States</hi> proſperity, beſides your love of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> your great courage, and your unparalleld actings, beyond any other in Authority, tending thereunto, with the many favours and great incouragements (to ſerve &amp; ſuffer for my Countrey, and not to fear nor be caſt down with the greatneſs of perſon) which I have received from you many years ſince, even when you were in a more private condition, &amp; finding no change in you, when thus eminently placed, yet no leſſe then your worth and ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue merit, are the inducements to preſent theſe my weake endeavours (which I have undertaken without any ſiniſter or by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ends, for the good of my poor <hi>Countrey</hi>) only to your <hi>Lorſhip,</hi> craving your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> favour, and that you will procure me pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and indempnity, while I proſecute the following charges, and other great diſcoveries which will bring to the <hi>State</hi> ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pounds and more; ſome whereof, of conſiderable values up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my own charge and travel, are already returned: if nothing elſe would ſpeak for me in excuſe, yet the very relation (of the barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, unmanly, and inhumane cruelty of <hi>Thomas Crayſtor</hi> Major of <hi>Carlile,</hi> and Lieut. Col. <hi>Briggs</hi> uſed towards one <hi>Trefena Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> wife of one <hi>Chriſtopher Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ter,</hi> then a Souldier in <hi>Carlile</hi> Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and now a <hi>Lieutenant</hi> of Horſe in the <hi>Army</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly for her judgment, croſsing <hi>Presbytery</hi>) would and will in ſome meaſure ſet forth the inviterate malice this <hi>Craiſtor</hi> (who is Sir <hi>Arthurs Viceroy</hi> of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> for all <hi>Officers, Juſtices</hi> of peace, and <hi>Cummiſſioners</hi> of the <hi>Militia Miniſtry,</hi> &amp; ſequeſtrations Sir <hi>Arthur H.</hi> wholly leaves to his nomination: and none muſt bear in any Office whom <hi>Craiſtor</hi> approves not)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117774:5"/>beareth towards ſuch as inclined not to the <hi>Presbytery</hi> and comply not with this <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Intereſt.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Trefina Carter</hi> this laſt ſummer living in <hi>Carlile,</hi> went into a viſited houſe, the ſame being unknown to her then, <hi>Crayſtor</hi> then Maj: of <hi>Carlile,</hi> hearing of it, bearing a grudge to her for her judgement, Commanded her to houſe, but not allowing any woman to be with her, being great with Child, and near her account, ſhe venturing forth for a pint of Wine, (another ſhe had not to ſend for it,) Lieut. Col. <hi>Briggs</hi> meets her, asked her, how ſhe durſt come out of her doors, contrary to the Majors Order, ſhe modeſtly replyed, if the Major would let ſome bring unto her what ſhe needed, (for ſhe had none with her) ſhe would not go out of her houſe, <hi>Briggs</hi> makes no anſwer, but draws his <hi>Rapier,</hi> offering to run at her therewith, with many execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Oaths, ſwearing he would have her out of Town, for it was the Majors pleaſure to have it ſo; he ſent her home with a file of <hi>Musketeers,</hi> and a Century is ſet at her door, to hinder any to come at her, ſhe falls in travel, the Midwife was ſent for, there being but one in the Town, who durſt not go, till ſhe knew the <hi>Majors</hi> pleaſure, he bids the <hi>Mid-wife</hi> go but tells her withall, if ſhe did, ſhe ſhould be ſhut up: the Woman is delivered after ſtrong labour, without Womans help, ſhe procured a Nurſe to keep her and her Child: but the fifth day after her delivery, the Major takes her <hi>Nurſe</hi> from her the Child and ſhe being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry weak, more likely to dye then live, and not any with her for none durſt but her own <hi>Nurſe,</hi> fearing the <hi>Majors</hi> diſpleaſure. In this extremity the poor Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was forced to riſe out of her bed, and goes to the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jors</hi> houſe, deſiring to know why he took her <hi>Nurſe</hi> from her; he anſwered for a Clenſer, is that your Conſcierce ſaid ſhe? the <hi>Major</hi> replyed, never ſtand queſtioning me, begone, we know your judgement; and till ſome honeſt Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of the <hi>Garriſon,</hi> went to the Major, hearing of this uncivil and unchriſtian uſage, the Major would not ſuffer any to come at her, though her houſe was never viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117774:6"/>and I hear the Woman is undone therewith, and inall likelihood will never recover her former health and ſtrength: thus you ſee my Lord, we complain not without cauſe, when <hi>Child-bearing Women</hi> in their travel, and <hi>Infants</hi> new born, are thus extreamly &amp; cruelly dealt with in thoſe parts for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe then their judgments, croſſing Presbytery; if theſe men will not pitty, nor ſpare <hi>Women</hi> and <hi>Children,</hi> but ſo vehemently perſecute them for their judgement, what can we expect from them, or you imagine they would do to us, if the Lord General being ſo near us, did not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I hope I need not further apologize, nor need ſay more to move you to pitty our condition, and help to eaſe and bring theſe your, and our enemies to account for rhe breach of their truſt, and the great oppreſſions and wrongs they have done to us and our Countrey, I will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to your view in the firſt place, the Petition and charge againſt Sir <hi>Arthur H.</hi> with the <hi>Articles</hi> exhibited againſt him, the Juſtices of peace, <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> of the <hi>Militia, Miniſtry,</hi> and <hi>Sequestrations</hi> in <hi>Cumberland,</hi> with <hi>Letters</hi> of the Congregated Church at <hi>Broughton,</hi> and other <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> to me, from ſome <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and other my ſuffering Friends, ſetting forth therein their miſery and ſad condition, &amp; after you have the Councel of the <hi>States Declaration,</hi> with my <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> upon the <hi>Declaration.</hi> And in the laſt place, my <hi>Letter</hi> to Sir <hi>Tho: Withrington,</hi> formerly printed, which relates to our former ſufferings, and how cunningly our Adverſaries have long undermined us, abuſed your Friends, &amp; ſuch as <hi>Parliament</hi> men as they thought favoured us, they drew Mr. <hi>Liſle,</hi> now one of the <hi>Lords Commiſſioners</hi> for the great Seal of ENGLAND, to make a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port againſt me, telling him I carried on a contrary Intereſt, and the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Deſign, and long it was before my Lord LISLE could be perſwaded I was a Friend; but upon better underſtanding, his prejudice againſt me was removed, and upon his motion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in the Houſe of COMMONS, after two years Impriſonment, I was ſet at liberty; and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117774:6"/>now (my Lord,) not doubting your favourable acceptance hereof, and your ready aſſiſtance in procuring me a fair hearing and tryal herein, I recommend my ſelfe and Cauſe to your Juſtice and Clemency, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Lordſhips obliged and humble Servant, JOHN MUSGRAVE.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>9.12. month 1650.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <pb facs="tcp:117774:7"/>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:117774:7"/>
               <head>TO THE Right Honourable the Councel of State, ſitting at <hi>White-hall.</hi> The Humble <hi>Petition</hi> of <hi>John Muſgrave,</hi> for, and in the behalf of <hi>Thomas Worſley Eſquire, John Worſley, Elizabeth Worſley,</hi> Captain <hi>Richard Cracken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorp, Mary Blaythwaite,</hi> and the reſt of the well-affected in the Counties of <hi>Cumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Weſtmerland, Biſhoprick,</hi> and <hi>Northumberland.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>Humbly ſheweth,</opener>
               <p>THat your Petitioner <hi>John Muſgrave</hi> above a year ſince, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated his own, and his Countreys ſad and diſtreſſed condition, and how the Enemies of this Common-wealth in thoſe parts do ſtill with unwearied and undefatigable en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours labour to carry on their deſigns, in ſtrengthening the hands of Malignants', and weakning the hands of your friends, and the better to effect wicked purpoſes got ſeveral incendiaries, and ſuch as have born Arms, and engaged againſt the Parliament in the firſt and ſecond war, and ſtill complies with the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> intereſt, to be Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of the peace, Sheriffs, &amp;c. and to have the whole authorities there in their hands, by which means they much Tyrannize, and oppreſſe your Petitioners, and the well-affected, and with leſſe difficulty may invite the Enemy into theſe parts.</p>
               <p>That this Honourable Councel upon reading the ſaid Remonſtrance declared, they would provide for your Petitioners relief, and redreſſe of their grievances, and upon another Petition unto this Honourable
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117774:8"/>Councel your Petitioner by the Articles thereto annexed, ſet forth how M. <hi>Charles Howard</hi> was made high Sheriffe of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> which Articles S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> undertook to examine, but wholy failed in the ſame. And the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> is ſo far from providing for your Petitioners relief, and the Countries ſafety as he hath of late procured ſuch as be Enemies to the Common-wealth to be Juſtices of the Peace, Sheriffes, Commiſſioners for the Militia, Miniſtry and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtrations; oppreſſing the well effected, and countenancing your Enemies, as appeareth by the Articles annexed, and exerciſeth an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary power without rule of Law, or Act of Parliament.</p>
               <p>That Sr. <hi>Willfrid Lawſon, Henry Tolſon, Thomas Curwen, Miles Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> Juſtices of Peace, contrary to an Act of Parliament, at the laſt Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Peace in the County of <hi>Cumberland</hi> fined one <hi>Lancelot Fearon</hi> 10. pounds for refuſing to ſwear upon a book, and the juſtices and Commiſſioners for the Militia there much oppreſſe the well affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and threaten to commit them for their meetings to prayer, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip, boaſting they have an order from S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> ſo to do.</p>
               <p>Your Petitioner humbly prayeth this Honourable Councel to take his long and chargeable attendance into conſideration, and put his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Remonſtrance, Petitions, Articles, with this Petition, and the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles annexed againſt S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge,</hi> in a ſpeedy way of exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, for relief and redreſſe of your Petitioners, and take a review of your own Declaration made upon your Petitioners former Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance. And humbly prayeth the benefit of preſenting of additional Articles as he ſhall ſee juſt cauſe, and that without delay or procraſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation for the good, and ſafety of this Nation.</p>
               <p>That the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge,</hi> the chief cauſe of all the preſent Northern miſeries, may be ſent for as a delinquent, to anſwer the ſeveral matters laid to his charge in the Articles annexed, and that at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming up, he may not be admitted to ſit as a Judge in his own cauſe, but ſtand in the capacity of a Delinquent, till he hath undergone his tryal, your Petitioner being ready at his uttermoſt peril to make good his charge, either before this Honourable Councel, or the high Court of Parliament.</p>
               <p>That all the other charges againſt <hi>Sheriffe Howard</hi> the Juſtices of the Peace, Commiſſionters for the Miniſtery, and Militia in <hi>Cumberland,</hi> may be put into a ſpeedy way of examination, and ſuch as ſhall be found un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit removed from their places.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:117774:8"/>
               <p>That <hi>Thomas Worſley,</hi> who is aged four-ſcore years, may have his Petition read and relieved, and that according to your Declaration up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your Petitioners Remonſtrance, your Petitioner, and ſuch Petitions as you declared to recommend to the Parliament may no longer be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, the Petioners being utterly undone by attendance. And laſtly, the Juſtices of Peace who contemned your Authority in fyning men for refuſing book-ſwearing contrary to the Act of Parliament made in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of tender conſciences, may be ſent for to anſwer their contempt, and proviſion made in the future that none in the Northern Counties be admitted, to execute civil Office in the adminiſtration of Juſtice, but ſuch as are known to be well affected to the preſent Government. And your Petioners ſhall pray as in their former Petitions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="articles">
               <head>Articles exhibited by <hi>John Muſgrave, Gentl.</hi> to the Councel of State, againſt <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Arthur Haſlerigge, Knight,</hi> and <hi>Barroner,</hi> Governour of <hi>New-Caſtle,</hi> and the Northren bordering Counties.</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions were brought in upon an Order of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of State dated the 31. of Iune 1649</note>1. THat S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> * contrary to his Engagement to the Councel of State, and Councel of States Declarations upon the Petitioners exceptions, procured lately ſuch in the County of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> to be Juſtices of the Peace, Commiſſioners for Sequeſtrations, Commiſſioners for the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and Commiſſioners for the Militia there as were known De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents, and ſuch as are diſaffected to the preſent Government, and complying with the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Intereſt, as by the charge againſt them hereunto annexed, and another charge againſt them, formerly exhibited to the Councel of State may appear.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> being the chief, and leading Commiſſioners for the Miniſtry at <hi>New-Caſtle,</hi> approved of ſuch Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in <hi>Cumberland</hi> at <hi>New-caſtle</hi> as refuſed the Engagement, were ſcandalous, and Delinquents; And ſuch Miniſters as were well affected, without any charge removed from their Miniſtery, and put them out of their places, whereby he diſcovers his diſ-affection to the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, by upholding and countenancing the Malignant party in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and keeping under the Parliaments friends, all which this Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117774:9"/>is able to prove, and further refers himſelf to the Copies of Letters hereunto annexed, the Originals being in the Petitioners hands.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> undertook to the Councel of State to examine the Articles exhibited by the Petitioner to the Councel of State, againſt M. <hi>Charles Howard,</hi> high Sheriffe of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> but negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the ſame, &amp; came privately into the Countrey to <hi>Naward</hi> and there feaſted with the ſaid Sheriffe, who is a dangerous, and moſt notorious Delinquent, as appears by the charge exhibited againſt him by the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioner to the Councel of State.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <note place="margin">Captain Howard is ſon to the Lord Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, a Member of the Councel of State, no Souldier, and never did any ſervice for his pay.</note>4. That the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> ſuffers Captain <hi>Howards</hi> Troop to lie upon free Quarter upon the Countrey, for theſe four Moneths laſt paſt, and doth coutnenance one <hi>Dobſon</hi> Captain <hi>Howards</hi> Lieutenant, who cheated the Troop of 1350. pound. And when com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint was made to S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge,</hi> he never puniſhed him for the ſame.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> gave Commiſſion to <hi>Edward Brigs,</hi> to be Lieutenant Colonel for <hi>Carelile</hi> Garriſon, and made him a Commiſſioner for the Militia &amp; Miniſtry in <hi>Weſt-merland,</hi> a man known diſ-affected to the preſent Government, and lately caſhered for his drunkenneſs and other miſcarriages by the now Lord General <hi>Cromwel.</hi> That the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur</hi> gave Commiſſions to <hi>Thomas Crayſtour,</hi> Cuth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert <hi>Studholme,</hi> Captain <hi>Brown,</hi> and others to be Captains, and Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants in <hi>Carelile</hi> Garriſon, men known to be diſ-affected to the preſent Government, profeſt Enemies to honeſt men, moſt of them having now laid down their Commiſſions, when they were to march into <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> And the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur</hi> doth countenance none in <hi>Cumberland,</hi> but ſuch as are profeſt Enemies to the honeſt party, and are for the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Intereſt.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That by the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur Haſlerigges,</hi> intruſting the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Militia in the hands of Delinquents, and men for the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Intereſt, the well-affected in <hi>Cumberland</hi> and <hi>Biſhoprick</hi> ly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der greater oppreſſions then formerly under King and Prelates. And the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur</hi> is a protector of Papiſts, and Delinquents, forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Subſequeſtratours, and Sollicitours for Sequeſtration in <hi>Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> to Sequeſter Papiſts Ordered to be Sequeſtred, of which the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and Delinquents do much boaſt, and honeſt men thereby are much caſt down.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:117774:9"/>
               <p n="7">7. That Sr. <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> hinders, and obſtructs the ordinary proceedings of Law and Juſtice in favour of Papiſts, and did take out of the Sheriffes cuſtody <hi>Ralph Lampton</hi> a notorious Papiſt and Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, being under arreſt, and formerly arraigned for poiſening his wife, with which <hi>Lampton,</hi> the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur</hi> is very kinde and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar.</p>
               <p n="8">8. That the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> procured <hi>Ralph Delivall</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> a Delinquent in arms againſt the Parliament, and diſ-affected to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Government this laſt year, to be high Sheriffe for <hi>Northumberland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. That the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> contrary to an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſuffered Lieutenant Colonel <hi>John Jackſon</hi> a notorious Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, and in arms againſt the Parliament, both in the firſt and ſecond War, a great plunderer to go and ride up and down the Countrey with his arms, and againſt law put the ſaid <hi>Jackſon</hi> in poſſeſſion of certain grounds and Colleries in <hi>Biſhoprick</hi> belonging to men well-affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, whom the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur</hi> by ſtrong hand diſpoſſeſſed, thereof without Law, and the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> againſt the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Law of the Land, moſt arbitrarily, and Tyrannically did by his power take from the now high Sheriffe of <hi>Biſhoprick</hi> the ſaid <hi>Jackſons</hi> goods taken in Execution after Judgement, and reſtored the ſaid goods to the ſaid <hi>Jackſon,</hi> contrary to all the rules of the Law.</p>
               <p n="10">10. That the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> is very familiar, and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth company with <hi>Thomas Wray,</hi> a Papiſt, in arms againſt the Parliament, and upon ſearch for a Popiſh Prieſt there was lately found in the ſaid <hi>Wrayes</hi> houſe Copes, and other Popiſh Relickes, and much Gold and mony, moſt whereof S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> cauſed to be returned back to M. <hi>Wrayes</hi> wife, a Papiſt. And the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur</hi> by his Souldiers put ſundry Honeſt men out of poſſeſſion of the Colleries ſettled upon them by Law, under colour the ſame belonged to the ſaid <hi>Wray<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> whoſe Debts S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> undertook to pay, (as <hi>Wray</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed) for the ſaid Colleries, being worth 10. pounds per diem, as the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur</hi> giveth forth to the utter undoing of the owners of the ſaid Colleries.</p>
               <p n="11">11. That the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> doth comply with, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance Colonel <hi>John Hilton,</hi> a Delinquent in arms, both in the firſt and ſecond War, and aſſiſts the ſaid <hi>Hilton</hi> to defraud the poor in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Pariſhes in <hi>Biſhoprick,</hi> of great legacies given by the ſaid <hi>Hiltons</hi> El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Brother.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:117774:10"/>
               <p n="12">12. That S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> brought Colonel <hi>Hacker</hi> into the Country, who contrary to an Act of Parliament Quarters his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and others under the name of Souldiers who are none, upon the well affected in <hi>Biſhoprick,</hi> and would but pay what they pleaſed, and in ſome places nothing, but upon complaint Colonel <hi>Hacker</hi> gave the people no relief, but threatned them to have them before S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur Haſlerigge</hi> for complaining, afterwards Captain <hi>Thomas Lilbourn</hi> brought the matter in queſtion before a Councel of War at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> but by Sr. <hi>Arthurs</hi> power it could never be fully heard, which if it had, there would have appeared many thouſand pounds kept wrongfully from the Souldiers, beſides the great oppreſſion of free Quarter, ſome Examinations whereof were taken by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Margets,</hi> which S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> keeps hitherto from reading, and the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur</hi> ſore threatned the ſaid Captain, for appearing for the Souldiery and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey againſt him, and Colonel <hi>Hacker.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. That the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> to diſable M. <hi>George Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourn</hi> to ſerve his Countrey, and the more to diſcourage the well effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in <hi>Biſhoprick,</hi> cauſed him to be put out of the Commiſſion of Peace, Miniſtery, and Militia, and much endeavoureth to Sequeſter the ſaid M. <hi>George Lilbourn,</hi> who hath commonly been reputed the moſt active, ſtirring, and ſuffering man for the good of this Nation, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Parliament began, and ſince of any that hath been, or is in the Countrey.</p>
               <p n="14">14. That Sr. <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> hath diſplaced all the well-affected men in <hi>Biſhoprick</hi> that were of the Committee for Sequeſtrations there, and put in their ſtead one <hi>Thomas Haſlerigge</hi> his Kinſman, and a ſtranger, and doth continue one Colonel <hi>Frauncis Wren,</hi> who in the head of his Regiment upon his firſt march into <hi>Scotland</hi> was diſgracefully, and juſtly caſhiered, by the now Lord General <hi>Cromwel</hi> for plundering, and other groſſe, and foulmiſde-meanours, and one <hi>Thomas Dalaval,</hi> an arch Malignant, and diſ-affected to the preſent Government, who lived in the Enemies quarters all the time the Earl of <hi>New-Caſtle</hi> had his Forces there.</p>
               <p n="15">15. That the ſaid George <hi>Lilbourn</hi> being Surveyer of the <hi>Biſhops</hi> Lands in <hi>Biſhoprick</hi> with one <hi>Edward Colſon,</hi> which ſaid <hi>Colſon</hi> joyned with one <hi>Saunders,</hi> and counterfeited M. <hi>Duncalfes</hi> hand without his privity for the abatement of a thouſand and odd pounds, meerly to cofin the State thereof, which cheat, and couſenage the ſaid <hi>George
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117774:10"/>Lalbourn</hi> diſcovered. But the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> much laboured, and Sollicited the ſaid <hi>George Lilbourn</hi> to conceal the ſaid cheat, and forgery of the ſaid <hi>Colſon,</hi> and though the ſaid <hi>Colſon</hi> be a man diſ-affected to the preſent Government, and married to a Papiſt, yet doth the ſaid S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> much countenance the ſaid <hi>Colſon,</hi> and made him a Commiſſioner for the Miniſtery, and his Court-keeper.</p>
               <p n="16">16. That your Petitioner hath been much Sollicited by the well-affected in his Countrey to preſent their grievances, and oppreſſions, and crave relief in their behalf, as appears by their Letters, Copies whereof are hereunto annexed.</p>
               <p n="17">17. That your Petitioner hath lately diſcovered ſundry concealed and unſequeſtred Delinquents of great Eſtates, which will bring in to the State, 10. thouſand pounds and more, if the Commiſſioners for Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtration made by Sr. <hi>Arthur Haſlerigge</hi> were honeſt, and faithfull men, but in regard moſt of the ſaid Commiſſioners are Delinquents, and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtrable themſelves, and all of them diſ-affected to the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, they do what in them lies to hinder your Petitioner in the proſecution thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="articles">
               <head>Articles Exhibited by <hi>John Muſgrave,</hi> againſt the Juſtices of the Peace, Commiſſioners for the Militia, Commiſſioners for the Miniſtery, and Commiſſioners for Sequeſtrations in the County of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> at the deſire and Requeſt of the well-affected there.</head>
               <p>INprimis, <hi>Thomas Lamplongh</hi> now Juſtice of the peace, a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner for the Militia and Miniſtry, took the Oath for the Earl of <hi>New-Caſtle</hi> againſt the Parliament, ſubſcribed the ſame ſet out Horſe and arms for the Enemy, Voluntarily contributed to the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and had his Eſtate protected by the Enemy, a great perſecutour of honeſt men, under the name of Independents, a countenancer and protector of Papiſts, Delinquents, and Malignant Miniſters, and did juſtifie the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Colonels Orders were good orders, and ought to be obeyed.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2. John Stoddert</hi> now a Commiſſioner for the Militia and Miniſtry, aman Sequeſtrable, was a Lieutenant in Arms for the enemies againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117774:11"/>under Captain <hi>Rolf</hi> a drunkard, a pleader for Delinquent and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Miniſters, an Enemy to honeſt men, and the Parliaments ſuffering friends.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3. Robert Hutton</hi> now a Commiſſioner for the Militia and Miniſtry, a man Sequeſtrable, took the Oath for the Earl of <hi>New-Caſtle</hi> againſt the Parliament, a countenancer and upholder of Malignant and ſcandalous Miniſters, and ſuch as Act for the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Intereſt, a common Ale-houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haunter and a great drinker.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4. Cuthbert Studholme</hi> now Commiſſioner for the Militia, Miniſtry, and Sequeſtrations, a private Captain in <hi>Carlile</hi> Garriſon, a Farmour of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtred tithes at far undervalues, when other would have given and offered greater ſums, a countenancer and upholder of ſuch miniſters as oppoſe the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, and he is for the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Intereſt againſt the Parliaments friends.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5. Thomas Craiſter</hi> now a Commiſſioner for Sequeſtrations for the Militia and Miniſtry, a profeſſed Enemy and perſecutour of all the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſuffering friends there, under the name of Independants, an upholder and maintainer of Malignant and ſuch Miniſters as refuſed the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and are for the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> faction, threatned thoſe that informed againſt ſuch, ſaying, they went in <hi>John Muſgraves</hi> way, he diſcountenanced wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes produced againſt <hi>Thomas Millington</hi> a Malignant Miniſter, who ſince the Act and Proclamations againſt King and Kingſhip, prayed for all Kings and Princes, and eſpecially for thoſe that pretended Title to this Nation, and for bad men to ſpeak againſt the King, and ſaid the Kings Laws would yet be in force and Lawfull, and that the Parliament could not order <hi>England,</hi> he doth ſtill Church women and take money for Burials, all this and much more was proved before the ſaid M. <hi>Craiſter,</hi> M. <hi>Langhorn,</hi> M. <hi>Lamplongh.</hi> M. <hi>Cholmeley,</hi> and <hi>Edward Winter,</hi> yet by M. <hi>Craiſter</hi> power, and Countenance the ſaid Miniſter is still Countenanced and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in his perſonage, being worth <hi>100. l. per annum,</hi> and more.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6.</hi> That <hi>Thomas Craiſter</hi> refuſed to joyn with the ſaid <hi>John Muſgrave,</hi> to receive diſcoveries againſt Delinquents, whereby the Common-wealth is hindered <hi>10000. l.</hi> and Delinquents inabled to raiſe a ſecond War.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7.</hi> That the Commiſſioners for the Militia in <hi>Cumberland</hi> ſuffer De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents to ride with their armes, and to go from their homes at pleaſure, ſome <hi>10.</hi> ſome <hi>20.</hi> ſome <hi>60.</hi> miles, without Sequeſtring or queſtioning them for it, contrary to the late Act of Parliament.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <hi>8. Thomas Cholmely</hi> now a Juſtice of Peace, a Commiſſioner for the Militia, Miniſtry and Sequeſtrations, a man Sequeſtrable left the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117774:11"/>for his delinquency in the firſt War, was in arms and joyned with the Enemy againſt the Parliament, and Voluntarily lent the Enemy fifty pounds, in the ſecond War kept Intelligence with the <hi>Scots,</hi> and ſent a man and horſe to the Enemy into <hi>Scotland,</hi> took the Oath for the Earl of <hi>New-Caſtle</hi> againſt the Parliament, a great Enemy to the Parliaments friends and them them call Independants, joyned with M. <hi>Briſcoe, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Wilfride Lawſon,</hi> M. <hi>Lamplongh,</hi> M. <hi>Henry Tolſon,</hi> M. <hi>Thomas Curwen,</hi> and M. <hi>John Barwis,</hi> in committing diverſe honeſt men for not coming to the Book of Common-Prayer, ſince it was taken away and cauſed them to be indicted at the quarter Seſſions for the ſame, and a little before the <hi>Scots</hi> received the laſt great overthrow by the now Lord General, the ſaid M. <hi>Cholmley</hi> ſaid the <hi>Scots</hi> were his brethren in Covenant, and it was againſt his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to fight againſt the <hi>Scots,</hi> he is a great upholder of ſuch Miniſters as are againſt the Engament, and he complieth with the Malignant and <hi>Scotiſh</hi> party.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>9. Edward Winter</hi> a man of a private condition, never appeared for the Parliament where danger was, a countenancer and maintainer of Malignant Miniſters, and ſuch as are againſt the Engagement, and procured by M. <hi>Craiſter,</hi> and M. <hi>Langhorn,</hi> to be a Commiſſioner for the Militia and Miniſtry to vote with them.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <hi>10. John Croſthwait</hi> a Commiſſioner for the Militia and Miniſters, a man that lived peaceably in the Enemies Quarters while they had power, never Acted nor appeared for the Parliament where danger was, holds his Eſtate in <hi>Tenantbright,</hi> under <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. John Lowthernant,</hi> and was Bailiffe and receiver of his Rents, when <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. John</hi> was a Commiſſioner of Array, he is a fearfull low-ſpirited man, and procured by M. <hi>Craiſter,</hi> to be a Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to vote and Act with him.</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <hi>11. William Mawſon</hi> now a Commiſſioner for the Militia and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, never Acted nor appeared for the Parliament where danger was, a great favourer and protector of ſcandalous and Malignant Miniſters, and procured by M. <hi>Craiſtor,</hi> and M. <hi>Langhorn</hi> to vote with them, and uphold their Intereſt.</p>
               <p n="12">
                  <hi>12. Thomas Langhorn,</hi> now a Commiſſioner for Sequestrations, the Militia and Ministry; a Man ſequeſtred took the Oath for the Earl of <hi>New caſtle,</hi> againſt the <hi>Parliament:</hi> A great enemy to them, they call <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents,</hi> refuſed to joyn with the ſaid <hi>John Musgrave,</hi> in diſcovery of <hi>Delinquents,</hi> when preſented unto them, an upholder of Mr. <hi>Balwyne,</hi> a Miniſter that refuſeth the <hi>Engagement,</hi> to preach on <hi>Thankſgiving-dayes,</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:117774:12"/>or preach for the <hi>Parliament</hi> or <hi>Army,</hi> diſaffected to the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and joynes with Mr. <hi>Craiſtor</hi> to keep under ſuch as favour the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> and ſuch as are called <hi>Independents.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">
                  <hi>13. Thomas Garth</hi> named <hi>Agent</hi> for Sequeſtrations, a man ſequeſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, took Oath for the Earl of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> was <hi>Cornet</hi> to Sir <hi>Henry Flet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher,</hi> and <hi>Quartermaſter</hi> to Sir <hi>Phylip Musgrave,</hi> a great favorer and protector of <hi>Malignants,</hi> while he was Solicitor to the old Committee for <hi>Sequeſtrations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">
                  <hi>14. Henry Robinſon,</hi> imployed as Agent for Sequeſtrations now by Mr. <hi>Craiſtor,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Langhorne,</hi> voluntarily gave to the Enemy five pounds to buy a Horſe, and ingaged he would never act for the <hi>Parliament,</hi> proteſting what he did for the <hi>Parliament,</hi> he did it for a livelihood; ſaying, alas, alas, he was for the <hi>King</hi> in his heart.</p>
               <p n="15">
                  <hi>15. Thomas Curwen,</hi> now a Justice of Peace, in the laſt Warre ſet out Man and Horſe for the Enemy, was protected in his Estate, by <hi>Baronet Curwen,</hi> and continued at the ſaid <hi>Baronet Curwens</hi> houſe, all the time of the laſt Warre, and after the County was reduced to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> he protected the ſaid <hi>Baronet Curwens</hi> Eſtate, kept his Goods from being ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring, and in a threatning manner, told ſome whom he called <hi>Independents,</hi> that it was ſuch as they that cauſed the laſt Warre.</p>
               <p n="16">
                  <hi>16.</hi> That all or moſt of the <hi>Delinquents</hi> there, injoy their real Eſtates, and moſt of their perſonal, and thoſe that have compounded with Sir <hi>Arthur Hazlerig,</hi> did not compound to the half value of their Eſtates.</p>
               <p n="17">
                  <hi>17.</hi> Sir <hi>Wilfride Lawſon,</hi> now a <hi>Commiſſioner</hi> for <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and a Juſtice of Peace, was a <hi>Commiſſioner</hi> of <hi>Array,</hi> and acted upon the ſame, took the Oath for the Earl of <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> and was in Arms with the Enemy, againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> hath great ſummes of money of the County, not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted for, a profeſſed Enemy to honeſt men, a favorer and Protector of <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Delinquents.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="18">
                  <hi>18.</hi> That the Commiſſioners for the <hi>Militia,</hi> are great favourers of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants</hi> very unequally raiſing the Horſe on the poorer ſort; and the <hi>Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aments</hi> Friends, whoſe Eſtates are under ten pounds <hi>per Annum;</hi> and men of great Eſtates, and charged by the Act, not charging them proportionably, and upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uch as have Eſtates, and did ſet out Horſe and Arms for the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, they impoſe little, and of ſome ſuch nothing at all.</p>
               <p n="19">
                  <hi>19.</hi> That the Commiſſioners for <hi>Miniſters</hi> have diſplaced ſuch honeſt <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> as they call <hi>Independents,</hi> and ſuch rectories they take into their hands, they farm out to their own Agents and Servants, at far underva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lues,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117774:12"/>and for far leſs then others would have given and afford, when the ſame we let out, as one instance for many, they let the Rectory of <hi>Graiſtock,</hi> which is worth <hi>300</hi> l. <hi>per Annum,</hi> to their Agent Clerk for threeſcore and eleven pounds, when twice as much was bid, and the Commiſſioners take the Tythes up to their own uſe, as can be proved.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>JOHN MUSGRAVE.</signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>The Articles are ſubſcribed, and will be atteſted by</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Nicholſon,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Mungo Rothew,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Nicholſon,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Francis Smith,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Iſaac Antrobus.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="order">
               <argument>
                  <p>My exceptions to the <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> for the <hi>Militia,</hi> upon this following Order, were approved by the Councel of State, and Sir <hi>Arthur H.</hi> beſides his <hi>Engagement</hi> to the Councel of State, promiſed me afterwards, he would put none others but honeſt men, in any place or Office; but hath done far otherwiſe.</p>
               </argument>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Die Jovis</hi> 31. <hi>January</hi> 1649.</date> At the Councel of State, at <hi>White-Hall.</hi>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>ORDERED,</p>
               <p>THat Mr. <hi>John Muſgrave</hi> be ſent unto, to come to this <hi>Councel,</hi> to morrow in the afternoon, to give in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, and the reaſon of thoſe exceptions which he makes againſt the names of the Perſons, given in by Sir <hi>Arthur Hazlerig,</hi> othe <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> for the <hi>Militia,</hi> for the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern</hi> Counties.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Yours,</hi> G. FROST, <hi>Secretary.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:117774:13"/>
               <argument>
                  <p>AFter Sir <hi>Arthur H.</hi> had conſented to by aſide, the Commiſſioners there for the Militia, whom I excepted againſt, I return into my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and acquainted my Friends what I had done, they much rejoyced, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring me in their names, humbly to repreſent to the Lord Preſidene <hi>Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw,</hi> their thankful acknowledgement of his former reſpects, which they and their Countrey had received from him, when in Eaſter Terme laſt, when being about ſome Lawes concerning my ſelf and my poor Mother oppreſſed by a bad Husband: I came to <hi>London,</hi> I found our affairs in a worſer condition then I expected; upon the Lord Gen. March for <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the <hi>Militia</hi> of this <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> being to be ſetled for the more ſecurity thereof, Sir <hi>Arthur H.</hi> procures a <hi>Commiſ.</hi> to the excepted perſons to be <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> for <hi>Cumberland,</hi> with which I was acquainted but few dayes before I was conſtrained upon urgent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, to return home, whither being come, this following letter is ſent me from the Congregated Church at <hi>Broughton.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Kind Friend and Brother <hi>Muſgrave.</hi>
                  </salute>
               </opener>
               <p>UPon your return from <hi>London,</hi> in <hi>Hillary</hi> Terme, we were much gladded the Councel of State was pleaſed to hear you upon your exceptions to the Commiſſioners of the Militia, and for their Declaration to redreſs our grievances complained of in your <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance;</hi> but when we underſtood that Sir <hi>Arthur Hazlerig</hi> had procured the ſame men whom you excepted againſt, not only to be Commiſſioners for the Militia, but for the Miniſtry, we were caſt down, conceiving the Enemy to be very potent, and prevailing more on you, becauſe of your negligence, though formerly you have been very active and ſuffering for your Countrey; yet in this we cannot but blame you, being confident, if the Councel of State had known what manner of men they were, how diſaffected to the preſent Government, either <hi>Cavaliers,</hi> or of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> faction, not one of them would have been approved of by the Councel of State, unleſs the Governor of <hi>Carlile</hi> who in regard he is a ſtranger, is wholly guided by the other: as for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117774:13"/>the Militia, they purſue not the Act, but take a diſpoſing power of mens Eſtates, ſetting ſome half a Horſe, where his Eſtate is not equal to ſuch they impoſe but a third part. And for the Miniſtry they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of few or none, but ſuch as are of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> faction and ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors againſt <hi>Independents,</hi> or if worſe may be, ſuch as are Malignants and Royaliſts; but for honeſt men, they cannot abide, ſuch they remove and put out of the Miniſtry, under the name of <hi>Sectaries</hi> and <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Lampit,</hi> Mr. <hi>Baggerley,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Wharton;</hi> if any be for the <hi>Presbytery,</hi> though they deny the Engagement, are approved of, and allowed: our Juſtices of Peace do impoſe book-ſwearing upon ſome of the States friends, and for denying the ſame, do fine them in ten pounds, threatning them, and ſcoffing them, and calling them as they think good. Mr. <hi>Muſgrave,</hi> be not weary of well doing, though you have no money or wages from us, ſlight us not, it concernes you nearly: if the Enemy be thus holden up, you can expect little eaſe, and leſſe ſecurity; therefore as you tender your own welfare, and your friends peace, be not ſluggiſh or longer ſilent, but ſtand for the cauſe of our God, and his People, be bold, it will be your Honour, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the ſucceſs be, truſt God. Sir, howſoever be our condition, we will not ceaſe to trouble you, hoping you will take in good part what we have written; and will not forſake your ſuffering friends, or in ſilence leave us under our Enemies hands, let the God of power inable you to finiſh what you have begun, for the good of his Church and People; to whoſe care and protection we recommend you and our cauſe, this</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>13. of the 9. Moneth 1650.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your Brethren in affection, and ſigned by the direction of the Church at <hi>Broughton,</hi> in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, viz. <hi>John Robinſon, Mungo Rothero, Gawen Wheelwright, John Taffin, Iohn Bow, Iohn Scot, Fran: Smith, Tho: Thomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Iohn</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letters">
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Lampit, <hi>the Miniſter of</hi> Aickton <hi>in</hi> Cumberland, <hi>hearing I was to take my journey for</hi> London, <hi>writes unto me this following Letter,</hi> &amp; <hi>after came to me himſelf, deſiring me to preſent his Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Councel of State, and another for the Committee for plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Miniſters; the man being poor, and a great ſufferer, I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook to do my endeavour, to accompliſh his deſire, but not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what ſucceſs I ſhould have, therein I did not take one peny of his money.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:117774:14"/>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>October</hi> 15, 1650.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <salute>Worthy SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>HEaring of your exceeding care in promoting the glory of God, &amp; of your favourable countenance in incouraging honeſt men, in reference to the State, and preſent Government of this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſtrongly animates, and makes me, though unacquainted, to preſent you in theſe lines, with a ſhort Character of the harſh, and unkind (if not unjuſt) dealings and proceedings of the Commiſſioners for the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry againſt me at <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> and their favour towards Malignants, and ſcandalous Miniſters. Sir, I was by ſome of the old Committee, and other Officers in <hi>Carliſle,</hi> commended to <hi>Aicton</hi> Church as Miniſter, &amp; (after the deceaſe of Mr. <hi>Halton,</hi> laſt incumbent) there elected &amp; called by the People, as appears by a teſtimony under their hands; but when Mr. <hi>Crayſtor</hi> had received the like Commiſſion, I was called at the firſt to <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> and their rage was ſo hot againſt me, in that I paſſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the notion of an <hi>Independent,</hi> that Mr. <hi>Crayſtor</hi> told me, I ſhould not ſtay at <hi>Aicton</hi> upon any condition, and ſo by his procurement, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> and the reſt, that they ejected me, ſequeſtred the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, and left the people ever ſince without a Preacher; they having neither information, accuſation, or other charge againſt me, ſave only my judgement, croſſing <hi>Presbytery</hi> and the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Intereſts. But as for others, whoſe names are ſubſcribed, though Malignant, known Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, and very ſcandalous, the Commiſſioners approved, and ſetled in their place as honeſt men, and others as yet never queſtioned. All which partial actings of theirs, as yet ſtrengthens theirs, and the hands of their enemies; ſo it mightily diſheartens the well affected, and will prejudice, as me in particular, ſo the Common-wealths friends in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral: Wherefore I pray you in behalf of my ſelf, and the honeſt party, uſe your endeavour for a ſpeedy redreſs, which I hope you will not neglect, and reſt,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Friend to ſerve you, W. LAMPIT.</signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:117774:14"/>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> Miniſter at <hi>Weſtword,</hi> who had two wives at once, now living, this they know.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Luggard,</hi> Miniſter at <hi>Workington,</hi> who was a <hi>Chancellour</hi> in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> was married to another mans Wife in her Husbands lifetime, and often drunk.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Jo. Mackmillian</hi> a <hi>Scot,</hi> who had an adulterous Baſtard in the higheſt degree, and was depoſed for it in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Johnſton</hi> Miniſter at <hi>Diſtington,</hi> who had often complyed with the enemy under Duke <hi>Hamilton.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Grainger</hi> Miniſter at <hi>Bromfield,</hi> who is often drunk, an apparent Malignant, and a <hi>Cavaleriſh</hi> Prieſt, even to this day.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Ratckleiffe</hi> of St. <hi>Bees,</hi> Mr. <hi>Sleddal</hi> of <hi>Cannanby,</hi> with many more whom they know themſelves, have been very active againſt the State, yet becauſe they are <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> they muſt be ſetled, and are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed in their places, by their power.</p>
                  <p>Mr <hi>Wheel-wright</hi> Chaplain to Barronet <hi>Curwen</hi> at <hi>Preſton,</hi> lately in Arms againſt the State, now Miniſter at <hi>Broughton.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Warwick</hi> late <hi>Chaplain</hi> to Sir <hi>Edward Musgrave,</hi> a great plunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of honeſt men.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Chambers</hi> at <hi>Allhallowes,</hi> tenderer of oath for the Lord <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle,</hi> a Preacher for the Enemy, a <hi>Common-Prayer-Book man.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Welchman</hi> Miniſter at <hi>Stannix,</hi> an enemy in <hi>Carliſle</hi> Town, when the Leager was againſt it, and many more.</p>
                  <p>And all the Sir <hi>Johns</hi> and Readers yet never queſtioned by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, and that the Independents firſt queſtioned, and put out, I have alwayes been in the <hi>Parliaments</hi> Army and Garriſon, and never declined the ſervice, being 3. times in priſon, and 5. times plundered, and I am now going with the Governor of <hi>Carliſle</hi> into <hi>Scotland</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours, <hi>W. L.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
               <trailer>To his much honoured Friend, Mr. <hi>Muſgrave,</hi> this deliver.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:117774:15"/>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>October the</hi> 16. 1650.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <salute>Dear friend,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>UPon after thoughts I am bold to acquaint you further with <hi>M. Craiſtours</hi> dealing and my friends, I being at <hi>New-Caſtle</hi> by order from the Commiſſioners for the Miniſtry, and knowing M. <hi>Crai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours</hi> reſolution to out me, I delivered a Letter that I received from Major <hi>Bird,</hi> Captain <hi>Cave,</hi> and other Officers, who writ in my behalf to a friend of theirs and mine, Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Hobſon</hi> by name, which Letter when he read, and ſpake with me, did go preſently to <hi>M. Craiſtour</hi> and others, and ſpake in my behalf to him, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed him to do for me according to his deſire, which was to eſtabliſh me in the place I was placed in by the Order you have to ſhow, and I ſpeaking with <hi>M. Craiſtour</hi> my ſelf he appeared very loving, and ſaid I ſhould that day be called, and he would be my friend, my friends and my ſelf believing him, conceived all to be as he pretended, and did reſt contented till that day was paſt, and at night he meeting with Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Hobſon</hi> told him he had accompliſhed his deſire in behalf of his friend, which was my ſelf upon his word, the Lieutenant Colonel ſent a Letter to Major <hi>Bird</hi> and other Officers, that my fiend (ſayeth he) and yours is eſtabliſhed in his place. But all this appeared to be meer diſſembling, onely to hinder my friends to ſpeak for me, till he did get an order to out me without any charge againſt me, and Sequeſtred the means, whether this be juſt and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous dealing I ſhall deſire all un-by-aſſed to Judge, and ſince, he and the reſt have had the Retorie in their hands, there hath not a Sermon been preached by their appointment. And I would have preached to the people though nothing I asked for my pains; yet <hi>M. Craiſtour</hi> ſaid it was not fit for me to preach, ſaying, I was a private man, becauſe the hands of the Presbytery were not laid on me, upon order I left the place, five weeks the Clergy read to the people by the Commiſſioners appointment, as he ſaith, but after five weeks ſeeing their condition and hearing them complain to me, I have preached to them theſe ſix weeks for nothing, but now I am going with the Army into <hi>Scotland, M. Howldſworth</hi> an Enemy to the State, was indeavoured to be put in the place by Comiſſary <hi>Sewel,</hi> but the people would not accept of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117774:15"/>him. I could acquaint you with much more of this, and the like, but I reſt</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours W. Lampit.</signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>I have preached this 20. years, and was both Miniſter and Governour in <hi>Lunde Iſland,</hi> and was never excepted againſt by the Army or real friends to it, or the State.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>W. L.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
               <trailer>To his much reſpected friend, <hi>Mr. JOHN MUSGRAVE.</hi>
               </trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mr. Bywater Chapline</hi> to the Governour of <hi>Carlile,</hi> a man of good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port writes to me this following Letter in approbation of what <hi>Mr. Lampit</hi> had writ, and <hi>M. Craiſters</hi> unchriſtian dealing with him.</p>
               </argument>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Noble Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> MAjor (meaning <hi>M. Craiſter,</hi>) <hi>quondam</hi> Captain, did (as I am in formed) chearfully bear Arms for the King in <hi>Carlile,</hi> yea, bought Arms with his own mony, after this he faced about to the Parl. party, and being impriſoned by the Royalliſts for it, by-and-by he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants the premiſes conſidered, for when <hi>Duke Hamilton</hi> appeared be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Carlile,</hi> offering him releaſe upon theſe tearms, <hi>viz,</hi> In caſe he would joyn with him and the Presbyterian party againſt England upon the laſt invaſion, it is reported that he manifeſted willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to receive freedom upon theſe tearms, for ſince he hath acted in that ſtream with a high hand by countenancing ſuch as are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream enemies to this preſent power, * ſpeaking words of divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the Parliaments Garriſon though he himſelf had Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion there; Nay,<note place="margin">As Mr. Bald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win who utte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> of the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſtrang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> expreſsions tending to ſtrife and div<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> his whole current was for the Scottiſh Intereſt with the Engliſh Parliament, for he kept his Commiſſion there, and received the ſweet of it, till he with others were deſigned againſt Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, but then layes it down under this ſpecious pretence that he could not in conſcience receive any more mony from the State, in that he could not, or had not done them any ſervice, becauſe of his Majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralty,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117774:16"/>but all this while nothing ſaid of making reſtitution, he was a friend to the Scottiſh Miniſter of <hi>Cockermouth,</hi> who refuſed to take the Engagement, he keeps in ſundry Town-Officers that refuſe the ſame, manifeſting by ſundry other actions that what ever his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention is, yet his intention is not for the preſent power. My dear love to your ſelf from him who is.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your and the Common-wealths ſervant <hi>J. Bywater.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Octob.</hi> 15. 1650.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>I do well approve of this other relation concerning Mr. <hi>Lampit,</hi> for Mr. <hi>Crai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> manifeſted as much harſhneſs as he could.</p>
               </postscript>
               <trailer>To his very good friend M. <hi>Muſgrave.</hi>
               </trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <argument>
                  <p>ALl men may ſee by this Letter of <hi>L. Fearon</hi> the rage of the Juſtices made by Sr. <hi>Arthur H.</hi> have againſt honeſt men, &amp; that the poor Church of <hi>Broughton</hi> complain not without cauſe what would not theſe Juſtices do, if Armed with Law and countenance by the higher power, when they thus deſpiſe the Acts &amp; Ordinances of Parliament? for it is more then a year ſince the Act for liberty to ſwear without layingh and on a Book was paſſed and publiſhed.</p>
               </argument>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Mr. MUSGRAVE,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Was ſommoned to appear at the laſt quarter-Seſſions of the Peace at <hi>Cockermouth</hi> where I did appear, and being returned to be one of the Jury, becauſe I could not ſwear upon a book, <hi>Mr. Henry Pearſon</hi> then Clerk of the Peace, fined me <hi>10.</hi> pounds, and would not ſuffer me to be of the Jury. I ſhall deſire you to help me, and other of our friends, who are troubled for the ſame, that we may have the benefit of the Act of Parl. concerning Book-ſwearing, <hi>Mr. Antrobus</hi> and <hi>Francis Smith</hi> are troubled for the like by <hi>Mr. William Tubman,</hi> Steward to the Earl of <hi>Northum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland</hi> in Egremont-Court, the Juſtices that ſate upon the Bench the laſt Seſsions when I was fined in <hi>10.</hi> pounds are <hi>Sr. Willfrid Lawſon, Henry
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:117774:16"/>Tolſon, Thomas Curwen,</hi> and <hi>Miles Halton.</hi> I pray you do this for us; for the Parliaments ſuffering friends are much oppreſſed by their Enemies, <hi>Sir,</hi> I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your loving friend</hi> Lancelot Fearen.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Lamplongh</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>the 15. of</hi> October <hi>1650.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <trailer>For Mr. <hi>John Muſgrave,</hi> Steward of the Honour of <hi>Peureth.</hi>
               </trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Appleby</hi> who writ this following Letter is a <hi>Cumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> Gentleman, and was forced through the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignancy of the Juſtices, and the Committee of his Country, and withdrew in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Yorkſhire.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>AFter my kind love to you preſented (though unacquainted) yet I conceive by my wife and ſon, they have been much behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to you, and if I had been intimate with you, when you had Sr. <hi>Willfride Lawſon</hi> in queſtion at <hi>London,</hi> I could have been a means to have accompliſhed your purſuit and deſire, and if occaſion here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after fall I will give you inſtructions, which I hope will yet work ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. Sr. I conceive my wife preferred a Petition by your advice and furtherance unto the Councel of State, whereof ſhe got no anſwer, ſo I heartily deſire to know the event thereof, and withall your adviſe and furtherance in the proſecution of my cauſes, for I have ſuſtained great loſſes and wrongs as any man in the Countrey, not onely from the Enemy; but from our Committee and Juſtices alſo, (<hi>meaning in</hi> Cumberland) I will juſtifie, and prove that great Delinquents and Papiſts have had, and ſtill have more favour from them then any real and well-affected perſons, who have adventured life and Eſtate for them in their ſervice. I intended to have been at <hi>London</hi> not long ſince, but the times have been very bad and difficult with us, but upon any notice from you I will not fail to be with you before this Tearm
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117774:17"/>end, (God willing.) So (good Sir) let me have your help, and upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of your anſwer expect me with all ſpeed.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Halton</hi> in <hi>Craven.</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>Octob.</hi> the 18. 1650.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Yours to ſerve you quantum in me. <hi>LANCELOTH APPLEBY.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>To his Honoured friend M. <hi>John Muſgrave,</hi> at <hi>London.</hi>
               </trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="declaration">
               <argument>
                  <p>I Could not without ingratitude and doing wrong to the Councel of State, who hath done ſo much for ſetling this Common-wealth in peace of ſecurity, but publiſh this their Declaration made upon reading my Remonſtrance.</p>
               </argument>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>Die Lune <hi>27. Auguſt. 1649.</hi>
                     </date> At the Councel of State at <hi>White-hall.</hi>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>UPon reading the Remonſtrance of <hi>John Muſgrave</hi> on the behalf of himſelf, and others well-affected in the Counties of <hi>Lancaſhire, Westmerland,</hi> and <hi>Cumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> particularly of <hi>Thomas VVorſley</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> 
                  <hi>Iohn VVorſley</hi> his ſon, and <hi>Elizabeth VVorſley</hi> his daughter, Capt. <hi>Richard Crakanthrop,</hi> and <hi>Mary Blaithwait</hi> widow; and upon hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mr. <hi>Muſgrave</hi> himſelf conſideration had of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters remonſtrated and deſired to be done.</p>
               <p>It is ordered and declared, That care ſhall be had and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of putting the particulars ſpecified into a way of exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination and redreſs, and the Councel will endeavours, that a Reformation ſhall be had of the grievances complained of; ſome of which, as that of putting the <hi>Militia</hi> into truſty hands, are already under conſideration; And this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel further declares, that they will uſe their endeavours, that the particular Petitions of Mr. <hi>Muſgrave,</hi> and the reſt, may be preſented to the Houſe, and there read and ordered: In
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117774:17"/>reſpect of the long attendance of the parties, as ſoon as with conveniency the ſame may be done, and as the publick affairs of the Houſe will permit.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Ex. Gualter Froſt, Secr.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="remonstrance">
               <argument>
                  <p>HEre (Reader) thou haſt my Remonſtrance it ſelf upon which the Councel of State made their Declaration.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>To the Right Honourable the Lord Preſident, and the Councel of State ſitting at <hi>White-hall.</hi> The Remonſtrance, and humble ſupplication of <hi>John Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave,</hi> for, and on the behalf of himſelf, <hi>Thomas Worſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> 
                  <hi>John VVorſley</hi> his ſon, <hi>Elizabeth VVorſley</hi> his daughter, Captain <hi>Richard Crackanthorp, Mary Blaithwait Widdow, Thomas Gibſon,</hi> and the reſt of the well-affected in the Counties of <hi>Lancaſter, Weſtmerland</hi> and <hi>Cumberland.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is not to be doubted but as Juſtice, and treaſure are the chief ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters of all Common-wealths, &amp; Kingdoms: ſo the neglect of the one by male-adminiſtration, and unduely raiſing, and miſpending the other, have ever proved fatal to the preſent Governours and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of States, as by wofull experience the greateſt Monarchs, and States often, but ever too late have found. The miſ-government of <hi>Eli,</hi> and <hi>Samuel</hi> ſons made <hi>Iſrael</hi> change their Government, as well as their Governours. <hi>Sauls</hi> miſorder transferred the Kingdom from his family to <hi>David,</hi> the great burdens, and many Taxes of <hi>Rehobeam</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the defection of ten tribes which never returned again to the houſe of <hi>David,</hi> and after few generations all Iſrael with their Kings, and Princes were diſplanted, and carried away into captivity for their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and injuſtice, and for that ſin the Scepter was taken from <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:117774:18"/>and they brought tributary to the <hi>Roman</hi> Common-wealth, as the Prophets complained in <hi>Judahs</hi> defection, and before their fall. Judgement was turned away backward, and Juſtice ſtood then afar off, for truth was fallen in the ſtreet, and equity could not enter, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 59.14.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rome</hi> then kept faith with nations, executed Juſtice and judgement, for which ſhe was a long time famous, and thereby became M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> over the whole world. But when ſhe began to oppreſſe, her Senators cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and partial in judgement; Soon followed the ruine of that long flouriſhing Empire.</p>
               <p>The Rebellion of the <hi>Moors</hi> of Granado proceeded from the like, the cauſe thereof being, no other then the contempt they were in with the natural <hi>Spaniards</hi> whom they call old Chriſtians, among whom the <hi>Moors</hi> lived in continual vexation, eſpecially by them of the Clergy, and the Offices of the inquiſition, and by the bad adminiſtration of juſtice, and the inſolencies of the Miniſters thereof; which war con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued near two years, being both dangerous and difficult, and if by the wiſdom of a Gold-ſmith which adviſed the King of <hi>Spain</hi> to ſend them a general pardon (none excepted) which Honourable condition the ſame then might have given an end to that Monarchy, as the Gold-ſmiths Councel gave an end to that war, the charge and loſſe was great, King <hi>Philip</hi> ſuſtained thereby he ſpent more; then 5. mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of Crowns, and the intereſt of private men, and the ſpoil, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peopling of the Countrey was ineſtimable, in which war above 30000. Chriſtians loſt their lives, as for the <hi>Moors</hi> that were ſlain of all ages and Sexes, the number cannot be ſaid. If theſe poor <hi>Moors</hi> had been intreated with more mildneſſe and humanity, without doubt the <hi>Spaniards</hi> might eaſily have kept them in obedience.</p>
               <p>But having ſaid ſomething of the Clergy, who have in all ages been the bontifieu of States, I can not paſſe over them without the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a cruel Edict, the Clergy of <hi>Spain</hi> procured againſt the poor Jews, the <hi>Kings</hi> Councel upon the reducing of the Kingdom of <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nado</hi> to Spains ſubjection made an Edict fair in ſhew, but of pernitious conſequence, whereby all the Jews that inhabited <hi>Leon,</hi> and <hi>Caſtile</hi> were injoyned to turn to the Chriſtian Religion, and be baptized within 3 Moneths upon pain of confiſcation of all their goods and perpetual baniſhment, this decree was received, publiſhed, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by the incitement and provocation (ſaith my Authour) of the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:117774:18"/>Prelates, and ſloathfull Paſtors, who contemned their charge of teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good, and wholſome Doctrine, and likewiſe by the Monkes, and other ſeditious Church-men; who deſired rather to deſtroy then to feed thoſe miſerable creatures, unto whom they were in perpetual deteſtation, and ſcandal by reaſon of their wicked and corrupt lives, whereby it came to paſſe that the name of God was prophaned and blaſphemed amongſt the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Mahumetans,</hi> who would rather have retired a thouſand leagues then to draw near to receive any reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious inſtructions from ſo irreligious a people, whoſe piety was but childiſh ceremonies, and external forms, their knowledge meer cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and deceit to maintain and increaſe their riches, eaſe, and unruly appetites, and their aime and end Honours and worldly glorie, with a popular opinion of wiſdom in the affairs of the world, the which was plain, and evident to people of underſtanding amongſt the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels.</p>
               <p>Therefore it behoved (ſaith my Author) ſuch ill-affected perſons, and no wayes diſpoſed to amend as were the Prelates of thoſe dayes to ſet forwards ſuch Councels, and to cauſe the King of <hi>Spain</hi> to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe courſes fit, and pleaſing to the devill who is a murtherer from the beginning, and Author of all ruine, and deſolation which hath been ſince practiſed in all places of Chriſtendom with very bad ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe.</p>
               <p>For torments, death, confiſcation of goods, and ſuch other like can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not beget<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a grain of faith in the heart of man whoſe ſeed is the word of God, the watering the holy works of unfained charity by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the heavenly Father, and the increaſe thereof the ſpirit of the Lord, but they may well bring forth Atheiſme, Hypocriſie, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair in abundance which are the offerings, the Enemy of <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt demands: thus far my Author.</p>
               <p>From the like doings it ſeems that ancient cuſtome grew amongſt the <hi>Biſcanes,</hi> not to ſuffer any Biſhop to come within their territories, the paſſage is very remarkable.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>King Ferdinand</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> to whom the cuſtome was unknown, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with a <hi>Biſhop</hi> there, was advertiſed of their cuſtome and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to ſend him back, the Peaſants, and poor Countrey people thinking the ground infected, whereupon the Prelate and his Mule did tread, were buſied for many dayes after, in ſcraping together the duſt of the high wayes which they laid up in heaps, and threw it after
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:117774:19"/>with curſes and imprecations into the Sea. The which certainly was not done without ſome myſtery, thoſe people being not void of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but Superſtitiouſly devout, as the reſt of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> were.</p>
               <p>Even in thoſe dark dayes for their cruelties, and oppreſſions, had the Prelates and their Clergy contracted to themſelves, ſuch <hi>Odium</hi> of the people.</p>
               <p>Here it will not be unſeaonable to mention <hi>Don Pedro</hi> of <hi>Portugal,</hi> Son to <hi>Don Alphonſo</hi> the fourth, who for his prudence, and equity pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed the name of Juſticer. This Prince ſo ordered his houſe, and train, that his officers were expreſly forbid to moleſt his Subjects, eſpecially purveyors not to take any proviſion for his houſe before they had payed the price which the ſeller demanded upon great pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties, yea, death in ſome caſes. Hearing that Advocates whom we call Lawyers, did multiply ſuits, as that of one, they often made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, he diſcharged and baniſht them all out of his Realm, and impoſed great puniſhments upon Judges that ſhould ſuffer themſelves to be corrupted with money or otherwiſe, yea, with loſſe of life and confiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of goods. He made many Laws for the ſhortning of fuits, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing fir men for Judges, cauſing his Ordinances, and Laws to be executed with rigour, he appointed great puniſhments for light of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences; And if any told him he was too ſevere, he anſwered it was the means to reform vice, and that it was pleaſant unto God; for if the wicked were not kept in awe with the fear of death, they would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be reſtrained with leſſer puniſhments, finally to have the good live in peace, it was neceſſary to puniſh the bad ſeverely. And as ſoon as the pleaders had made their demands, and pertinent anſwers given, they were preſently diſpatcht if it might be. If by any tricks and deviſes matters were delaid, the offenders were puniſht, that is, the poor by the whip, and the rich by fines, by reaſon whereof his Realm flouriſht in peace, and abundance of all things: and he was Honoured, and beloved of his Subjects as much as any prince living; he had often the ſaying of the Emperour <hi>Titus</hi> in his mouth, that he held the day loſt wherein he had not done good to ſome one, he was more ſevere to his houſhold-ſervants then to any other; he cauſed a Secretary to be ſlain, having taken money without the privity of his Treaſurer.</p>
               <p>But it happened far otherwiſe with wicked, and bad Princes, who not onely bring deſtruction upon themſelves, and families, but cauſes
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:117774:19"/>the change and alteration of the Government it ſelf, as <hi>Rome</hi> did; who after they had baniſht <hi>Tarquine,</hi> their laſt King for his Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, conferred the Government of the State upon <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Collatine,</hi> but becauſe the name of King was odious for their wickedneſſe in their ears, they changed the manner of Government from perpetual to annual, and from a ſingle Government to double; leaſt perpetual, or ſole domination, might be motives to uſurpation.</p>
               <p>Theſe we mention not that we conceive you are ignorant thereof. but that in them we behold how our good God in all ages, and times hath puniſht, and dealt with Tyrants, and oppreſſours, and his mercifull diſpenſations towards, and the many favours and temporal bleſſings he hath beſtowed on good Princes, and Governours though Infidels, and Aliens from the faith of our Lord Jeſus.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing the Lord of heaven and earth by your Councels hath thrown down the ſtrong men of <hi>Babel,</hi> and removed thoſe who by new Councels would again have ſet up our old Task-maſters in a more ſpecious, but far more dangerous, and deſtructive way then the common Enemy ever projected, even to be done by a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>This Nation having received ſo great benefit by your Councels, we are humbly bold to make our addreſſes unto you for relief, having affayed all other known wayes and means.</p>
               <p>We under God do repoſe the hope and remedy of our afflictions, and redreſſe of our grievances in the Juſtice and bounty of this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Councel; in which reſpect, as well on the behalf of our poor Countrey as our ſelves, we begge, and intreate you to caſt your eyes of mercy upon our afflictions, to cure our griefs, and redreſſe our grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, with timely, and ſeaſonable remedies, agreeable with your wiſdom and Juſtice. We never were Refractory to your Commands, we hold that belonging to our duty and fidelity which depends upon your Authority, or reſpects your ſecurity. We beſeech you let our tears, the true demonſtration of our ſorrow induce you to defend us againſt the oppreſſions of thoſe who by Oath, and action joyned with the Enemy, while he had ſtrength againſt you; and now in a more ſecret way labour to weaken you, and again ſet up the Enemy by ruining your friends, and oppreſſing the Countrey.</p>
               <p>We hope our neceſſities, and poverties will not make you leſſe willing to hear our complaints, &amp; do us Juſtice: for he gives a grievous
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:117774:20"/>ſentence againſt the State of mans mortality, that denieth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion to men in miſery, and your Honour, and Juſtice makes us aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured that you will not reject us, becauſe that we are men afflicted, it being not onely piety, but good pollicy to miniſter ſuccours to men in neceſlities, and to relieve ſuch as ſuffer, and expect it: your glorie being more to relieve the oppreſſed then to conquer our Enemies; for as the one is juſt, and neceſſary for your ſecurity, ſo the other is an high Act of charity, and Juſtice, and thereby you become Maſters of affections.</p>
               <p>We will therefore with all humility preſent to your view a ſhort Narrative of our State and condition, and clearly demonſtrate unto this Honourable Councel, how the Authorities of thoſe Counties are put into the hands of the known and profeſſed Enemies of this State and Common-wealth, by whom we are as much oppreſſed, and kept un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as ever we were formerly under the Enemy.</p>
               <p>In the beginning of this war, the Juſtices of the Peace, &amp; Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Array in <hi>Cumberland</hi> &amp; <hi>Weſtmerland,</hi> the more eaſily to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive or affright the people, cauſed all ſuch as they ſuſpected to favour the Parliament and their proceedings, to be impriſoned, indicted or bound to the good behaviour,<note place="margin">For not coming to Church &amp; Common-prayer.</note> either upon the * ſtatute 23. <hi>Eliz.</hi> or for refuſing the Oath of Supremacy, the Earle of <hi>New-Caſtles</hi> Oath, or for not taking up Arms with them. Of whom firſt impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned were <hi>John Muſgrave,</hi> and Captain <hi>Richard Crackenthorp;</hi> by whoſe boldneſſe and conſtancy in bonds, and ſufferings, Mr. <hi>Oſmotherley</hi> with 2000. men in <hi>Cumberland</hi> declared againſt the Commiſſioners of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray,</hi> aſſociated themſelves together, and for half a year could not be reduced under the Commiſſion of <hi>Array,</hi> till by the treachery of Sir <hi>Wilfrid Lawſon,</hi> they were delivered up into the Enemies hands, and then <hi>Lawſon</hi> uſed great cruelty againſt ſuch as were for the Parliament there.</p>
               <p>And that the Enemy might uphold their intereſt the better, in caſe the Parliament prevailed, by agreement and combination, Sr. <hi>Wilfrid Lawſon</hi> with the new Committee ſeemed to diſaffect the <hi>Kings</hi> party, for which they were confined to their Chambers, but it was meer diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation, for after few dayes they were the men in favour, and great promoters of men and money for the Enemy, and cruel perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutours of the Parliaments friends.</p>
               <p>Upon the reducement of <hi>Cumberland</hi> to obedience of Parliament,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:117774:20"/>Sir <hi>Wilfrid Lawſon</hi> procured himſelf to be made Commander in chief over the Forces raiſed there, by which he and the Committee protected the Delinquents, and more oppreſſed the Countrey then ever the Enemy did, the better to colour their doings, the whole Committee, being Delinquents and of the Enemies faction procured an Order from the Commiſſioners of Parliament, to ſuſpend all Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtrations, which was done accordingly, in the mean time raiſing great ſums by way of Loan, without order or Ordinance of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, beſides all other Taxes, whereby they made the commonalty like diſaffected as themſelves. And to prevent any of the Parliaments friends from having any Authorities there, it was upon private and ſerious debate reſolved betwixt them and the Parliaments Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, that ſuch as had acted, or ſuffered for the Parliament, being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Independents, ſhould not be any wayes truſted or imployed: two Moneths after the County was reduced, and the Commiſſioners of Parliament gone thence, the Committee underhand incouraged the Papiſts and the Countrey to take up Arms to raiſe the ſiedge of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lile,</hi> and furniſhed the Enemy within <hi>Carlile</hi> with all manner of proviſion, and the Countrey people with ſhot and pouder upon their declaring againſt the Parliament. That all Officers under Sr. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frid Lawſon</hi> were profeſſed and ſworn Enemies to the Parliament, and had been Officers and Captains before for the Kings party, Sr. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frid Lawſon</hi> had from Sr. <hi>Philip Muſgrave</hi> 20. Horſe to protect, which he returned to him again, a little before Sr. <hi>Philip Muſgrave</hi> did riſe laſt againſt the Parliament. Of all which the well affected complained to the Parliament, but their Agents through the countenance of ſome in Parliament were caſt into priſon, whereupon the well-affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ſent their Petition to the Parliament, for releaſing their Agents, and redreſſe of their grievances, but could never to this day get the ſame preſented. The Committee ſent complains to the Parliament, how the number of Independents and Sectaries increaſed thereby to make eaſier way for the Enemy &amp; the Lord <hi>Digbies</hi> coming into thoſe parts, upon whoſe coming <hi>Lawſon</hi> deſerted the Countrey, and made no reſiſtance; After the <hi>Kings</hi> coming to <hi>New-Caſtle</hi> into the <hi>Scots</hi> Army, <hi>Lawſon</hi> went to kiſſe the <hi>Kings</hi> hand, and then he and the <hi>Scots</hi> confederated together (whom before he ſeemed to oppoſe, to ſuppreſſe the Armies friends, and indicted ſixteen at one Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions for not coming to the book of <hi>Common-prayer,</hi> and others
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:117774:21"/>they fined for refuſing to ſwear upon a book, and others they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</p>
               <p>That Sr. <hi>Wilfrid Lawſon</hi> being ſummoned to appear before the Committee of Indemnity to anſwer his Delinquency, his friends in the houſe of Commons provided an Order to the contrary, and for his ſtay in the Countrey; which he received ten dayes before he left the Countrey, and came to <hi>London</hi> under colour to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer his charge: but before he came away, he cauſed all the Arms of the Countrey to be brought into his Iſle upon the Counties charge, and made Governour thereof one <hi>Bewley,</hi> a vain drunken man, and one that was diſaffected to the Parliament, who ſhortly after delivered up the ſame with the Arms therein, to Sr. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Muſgrave,</hi> and <hi>Richard Muſgrave, Lawſons</hi> brother in Law, and though <hi>Lawſon</hi> raiſed great ſums of money for maintenance of 30. men allowed him for the Iſle, he kept but 3. who upon the firſt ſummons delivered it up, upon Sr. <hi>Philip Muſgraves</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into the Countrey with 16. Horſe at moſt: the Committee gave him way to muſter the Countrey without making any reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and <hi>Carlile</hi> was taken in by 17. men, which could never have been but by the treachery of <hi>Lawſon,</hi> and the Committee.</p>
               <p>While <hi>Sr. Philip Muſgrave</hi> thus raiſed men and money by the Committees compliance, <hi>Lawſon</hi> and Major <hi>Barwis</hi> he here at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and under pretence of their preſent going down, got orders for auditing their accounts, amounting to many thouſands, which they ſold; whereas in truth they had raiſed double the pay upon the Countrey, and then lay a long time in <hi>London</hi> privately, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving cauſed the Parliament to be made acquainted, they were gone into <hi>Cumberland,</hi> while they were here in Town and whither they never went till after <hi>Preſton</hi> battel.</p>
               <p>That though <hi>Sr. Wilfrid Lawſon</hi> was not in Commiſſion in his travel from <hi>London,</hi> he with his Lady, and ſervants took free quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and Countrey mens Horſes from them in <hi>Biſhoprick.</hi> And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſurrender of <hi>Carlile</hi> to <hi>Sr. Arthur Haſlerigge,</hi> he procured Captain <hi>Fenwicks</hi> Horſe to raiſe him great ſums of money of the poor Countrey people for his pretended loſſes, having no Order nor Act of Parliament for ſo doing, whereof one of the brethren of <hi>Mr. Serjant Birket,</hi> came to the Parliament to complain, but the bad ſucceſſe others had before in the like eaſe deterred him, and ſo he returned without relief or redreſs.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:117774:21"/>
               <p>That Sr. <hi>Wilfrid Lawſon,</hi> and the Committee to keep the favour of Sr. <hi>Philip Muſgrave,</hi> ſuffered his Lady to enjoy her Husbands Eſtate under colour of farming the ſame, till Duke <hi>Hamleton</hi> came into <hi>Cumberland.</hi> Sr. <hi>Wilfrid Lawſon</hi> did for a long time take the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of <hi>Roſe</hi>-demeſnes part of the <hi>Biſhop</hi> lands to his own uſe, whereof we came to the Parliament to complain: But the Knights, and Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes who ſerved for thoſe Counties, were ſo far from aſſiſting us to get our grievances redreſſed as to this day not one of them would ever yet preſent a Petition for us. All ſuch as were Countreymen for their Delinquency having ſince left the Houſe; but when any Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents of the County came to compound at <hi>Gold-ſmiths hall,</hi> they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wanted ſome of our Parliament men to attend them thither, and Sollicite for them.</p>
               <p>The Earl of <hi>Northumberland</hi> who hath had 10000. <hi>l.</hi> for his pretended loſſes, procured Mr. <hi>Allen,</hi> a Gold ſmith of <hi>London</hi> to be elected Burgeſſe of <hi>Cockermouth</hi> in <hi>Cumberland,</hi> who though he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed better things would not preſent a Petition for any of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments friends there. Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> hath had Widdow <hi>Blaithwaits.</hi> Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in his hands more then three years, yet unpreſented, who after ſhe had attended above two years, returned home without relief. M. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> kept the Petition of <hi>Thomas Gibſon</hi> in his hand near two years, a man committed by the Commiſsioners of <hi>Array,</hi> and laid in irons for the Parliaments cauſe, the poor man was glad to return home with nothing but empty promiſes from Mr. <hi>Allen,</hi> to bear his changes near 300. Miles. Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> kept the Petition of <hi>John Muſgrave</hi> and Captain <hi>Crakanthorp</hi> ſo long as glad they were to take it from him. Yet doth the ſaid Earl imploy, or intruſt not any there in any Office, but ſuch as are profeſſed Enemies to the Parliament. And when the Earl was deſired to preſent ſome Petitions to the Houſe or Lords for ſome diſtreſſed in <hi>Cumberland,</hi> he refuſed to do the ſame, ſaying, the never preſented any ſuch thing</p>
               <p>By the Earles imploying of the grand Enemies of the Common-wealth, and Mr. <hi>Allen.</hi> neglect of his duty, the Parliaments friends there ſtill lie under greater oppreſſions then when the Enemy was poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of the Countrey.</p>
               <p>Sr. <hi>Wilfrid Lawſon,</hi> and the Committee with the countenance of Mr. <hi>Howard,</hi> who raiſed two Troups for the Enemy under <hi>Duke Hamleton,</hi> and reſorted to the Enemy in <hi>Carlile,</hi> and ſent them
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:117774:22"/>Veniſon, and other preſents, by the Votes of Malignants of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lile</hi> of late got the Lord <hi>Howard,</hi> Mr. <hi>Howards</hi> Father in Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned Burgeſſe for <hi>Carlile,</hi> and thereby they doubt not but to uphold their intereſt ſtill, knowing the Lord <hi>Howard</hi> will not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent any thing to the Parliament, whereby the oppreſſed Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and diſtreſſed friends of the Parliament may obtain any Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice from the Parliament, as we have found the ſame too true by ſad experience: for being ſollicited to preſent ſome Petitions to the Parliament for ſome of the Parliaments ſuffering friends after ſeveral dayes attendance he deſired to be excuſed, for he would not preſent the ſame.</p>
               <p>So that without the aſſiſtance of your good Lordſhip, and this Honourable Councel, the well-affected of thoſe Counties are hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ever to come from under the oppreſſion of their Enemies; all Authorities there being in the hands of the ſworn and profeſſed Enemies of the Common-wealth, ſome of the Committee there now reſiding in this Town, being Juſtices of the Peace, and having other great places, and Offices of truſt, upon their coming thence, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared they could not now Act with the Parliament, which was the cauſe of their leaving the Countrey, as they have ſaid to ſome of their friends here.</p>
               <p>There is not a Committee-man in <hi>Cumberland,</hi> nor Juſtice of Peace in either County, <hi>Cumberland</hi> or <hi>Weſtmer-land,</hi> ſaving one or two at the moſt, but many wayes have diſcovered his Malignancy and diſaffection to the preſent proceedings of this Parliament.</p>
               <p>And without the ſame be prevented, it will be a means to draw an Enemy thither, knowing they ſhall have no reſiſtance; <hi>Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi> the next adjacent County who by their Petition to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament againſt Sectaries ſubſcribed with 12000. hands, have manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted their diſaffection, will be upon all occaſions likewiſe ready to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain an enemy thence: not a Member of the houſe there would ever yet preſent Mr. <hi>Worſley</hi> and his childrens Petition unto the Parliament, who by the oppreſſion of wicked Judges, and the Prelates perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are ruined in their Eſtates, and every year have their goods ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away for their non-conformity to the book of Common prayer, as in the Prelates dayes, and to add to their affliction, ſome Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment men there, namely Mr. <hi>Holcroft,</hi> have baniſht them the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey for Sectaries, and by his Souldiers ſeiſed their rents there, for
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:117774:22"/>theſe five years, and ſtill take up the ſame, being demanded by what Authority they did take up the Rents there? Captain <hi>Holcroft</hi> held out his Piſtol, and ſaid here is our Commiſsion.</p>
               <p>All which is fully and truly ſet forth in their Petition; which doings, and the like oppreſſions have brought the wrath and judgments of God upon the Parliament, even by breaking them twice with their own ſtrength.</p>
               <p>But the Lord hitherto hath preſerved the Nation from breaking, by his righteous judgements upon the Parliament. We therefore hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſupplicate your Honours, to whom we fly for refuge and help, as the laſt, and viſible means under God for our recovery, in this our loſt and periſhing condition, having not onely fruitleſly ſpent above five hundred pounds in attendance upon the Parliament, but lie open to the mercileſſe cruelties of our adverſaries, and every day in danger to be ſurpriſed by the common enemy.</p>
               <p>If you neglect us, the ſame may likewiſe indanger your ſafety as our ruine, and haſten the curſe upon you which as a Milſtone is fallen upon the late King, his Houſe, &amp; Pears, &amp; which you can no other way avoid, then by your equal, and due adminiſtration of juſtice to the poor as to the rich, &amp; which in all probability will break factions, and recover un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you the loſt affections of the people, and raiſe again the drooping ſpirits of your oppreſſed diſtreſſed friends, and prevent the adverſary of his purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Now the better to facilitate this great work, ſo long retarded by ſome corrupt Members of Parliament, where, if not by your all delayes, and obſtructions of Juſtice ought to be examined, and redreſſed.</p>
               <p>It will not be amiſſe here to relate the expedient the wiſdom of our Anceſtors found out to prevent the delay of Juſtice, and not to be left onely to the will of private and particular Members of Parliament, when, and how to bring in Petitions as now is practiſed, to the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and great ſcandal of the preſent Government, ruin not onely of private families but of whole Countreys, and which hath rendered the Parliament to be no other then upholders of Injuſtice, &amp; ſupporters of Tyranny and oppreſſion, far contrary to our exſpectation and their promiſes and engagements; and which neceſsitated his <hi>Excellency</hi> and Armies to advance to <hi>London</hi> twice againſt them.</p>
               <p>The old and good way of bringing in Petitions into the Parliament for the equal diſtribution of Juſtice to all Suitors, was not by the <hi>Speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:117774:23"/>or any particular Member thereof, but by the Maſters of the <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery,</hi> who by their place, and Office were to attend the Parliament for that very end and purpoſe, as the <hi>Rolls,</hi> of moſt times witneſſe, it being by the old <hi>mod. tenend. Parliament</hi> and others accounted againſt reaſon, that Petitions ſhould be taken, &amp; brought into the Houſe by thoſe that were to debate, and determine them, for ſo might they at pleaſure keep them out, or too happily preſs them on; Therefore ſaieth the ſame Author, Petitions were filed in courſe, and ſo to be debated as they were received; which were intruſted to the care of known and ſworn Officers of the Kingdom, who of old time were appointed for triers of Petitions to enquire of the matter of fact expreſſed in the Petitions, that it might be rightly ſtated before it came to be debated in the Houſe.</p>
               <p>By the diſuſer whereof Juſtice hath been obſtructed, &amp; the ſame hath brought contempt upon the Parliament, &amp; no means left us for making known our grievances; and to compleat our miſery, the worſt of men again creep into Magiſtracy, by which they do the Parliament more diſſervice then when they openly acted in the way of profeſſed enmity; as by this enſuing ſtorie of a cunning welch Judge will appear.</p>
               <p>A Gentleman ſuſpecting the welch Judge to have been the cauſe of putting ſeveral of the Parliaments friends out of Commiſſion of Peace, and others known diſaffected, and delinquents to be in their place, did entertain diſcourſe with a boſome friend of his, by way of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining.</p>
               <p>The Gentleman ſaid the Judge was ever taken for a friend to Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers, and it was not well taken that he had put <hi>A. M.</hi> from his practiſe for <hi>A. M.</hi> was truly the Kings friend: the other repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſaid if it were ſo, the Judge ſhould bring him again to his pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, for he loved the King, and never was man ſo caſt down as he and his Son were for the Kings death, both of them wept bitterly when the King died; then ſaid the Gentleman, but I fear the Roundheads will complain of the Judge for putting them out of Commiſsion, and the Kings friends in their place, and ſo the Judge might come into trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and be leſſe able to ſerve his friends: the other anſwered, take no thought for that: as he waited all opportunities to do good Offices for the King and his friends, ſo he doubted not but to come fair off, if Roundheads did complain of him; for a Parliament man (whom he then named) would own the thing as his own act, who was able to deal with all that ſhould oppoſe.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:117774:23"/>
               <p>By all which your Lordſhip and this Honorable Councel may clearly perceive what imminent danger you are ſubject unto by theſe petty Tyrants of the time, who as they oppreſſe us, ſo they wait but for an opportunity to remove you from your ſeates.</p>
               <p>Now we leave it to your conſideration, if delay of Iuſtice be adenial of Iuſtice, or rather Injuſtice it ſelf, how unjuſt men be theſe our Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Gentlemen of the Houſe of Commons, who ſince the Parliament began would never preſent a Petition for us? ſome of us having ſince the third day of the Parliaments firſt ſitting down attended, and ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for that purpoſe, therefore as you tender your own ſafetie, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard you Honors, reſpect Juſtice, love the Common-wealth, and are affected with any bowels of compaſsion towards a diſtreſſed, afflicted, and oppreſſed people, take our Remonſtrance into your ſerious conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, with theſe our humble requeſts.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That all Delinquents in the North according to Ordinance of Parliament may be removed from all Offices Civil and Martial, and that under a penalty.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the Moneys unduly leavied by Sr. <hi>Wilfrid Lawſon</hi> or any others with us, upon the Countrey without order, or Ordinance of Parliament, may be accounted for, and ſatisfaction made to the parties wronged.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That Mr. <hi>Worſley</hi> and his childrens ſufferings may be taken into conſideration, and relieved, and proviſion made that for their non-conformity to the Book of Common-Prayer, they be not further moleſted either in their Perſons, Lands, or goods, all charges charged, and iſſuing out of the Exchequer againſt them for the ſame may be diſcharged, and nulled, and the burthen of Book-ſwearing taken away.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That <hi>John Muſgrave,</hi> Captain <hi>Richard Crackanthorpe, Mary Blaithwaite,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Gibſon,</hi> who are waſted with a long and charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able attendance, may have fitting repairations for their loſſes, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, by the Commiſsioners of Array, Juſtices of the Peace, and Committee-men of <hi>Cumberland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. That Mrs. <hi>Vaux</hi> Petition, with the Houſe of Peers Order upon it, may be taken into like conſideration.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That <hi>John Muſgrave</hi> for his diſcovery of concealed Delinquents in <hi>Cumberland,</hi> and his attendance upon the Committee of Lords and Commons for ſequeſtrations may be taken into conſideration.</p>
               <p n="7">7. That a way may be provided, that the grievances of our Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:117774:24"/>Counties &amp; the oppreſſions of the <hi>Juſtices</hi> of peace &amp; <hi>Committees</hi> there may be removed, and ſuch as have unjuſtly ſuffered by them may be repaired; to the end, we may not be conſtrained after 300. miles tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell hither, to conſume the little that is left us by the adverſary, in a fruitleſs and chargeable attendance for moneths and years, as for theſe 8. years and more we have done, upon ſuch men as will not, nor ever did preſent a <hi>Petition</hi> for us, themſelves: for the moſt part having by ſome irregular way, &amp; undue election by the votes of <hi>Malignants,</hi> or Letters of ſome petty Tyrants, or Lord, being returned Knights and Burgeſſes for our Counties.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>JOHN MVSGRAVE.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <argument>
                  <p>This following Letter I writ to my Lord Preſident, who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſent for me, and ſhortly after procured me audience before the Conncel of State upon reading my Remonſtrance, which I at the requeſt of ſome friends, have publiſhed as in thankfulneſs to his Lordſhip, ſo to ſatisfie and inform friends, how and for what Intereſt I have ever acted and ſuffered.</p>
               </argument>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>SInce my Letter to you by Mr. <hi>Rumſey,</hi> of the <hi>18.</hi> of the firſt moneth, I did forbear any wayes to be troubleſome unto you, neither would I now (if I could) have found a door open unto me for juſtice, which hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto as to me and my ſuffering friends, hath been altogether ſhut up.</p>
               <p>And now I am conſtrained, as the moſt probable means to attain my wiſhed deſires, to make my ſupplication to you, and though I could not in ſpirit go along with you in your laſt actings towards the late King, by the reaſon of the many oaths, and engagements made, and taken on his behalf; yet I have ever held it my duty, to ſubmit without reſiſtance to ſuch Powers
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:117774:24"/>and Authorities as the Lord of Heaven in his wayes ſhall ſet over us, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cirding to the Apoſtles Rule, <hi>Rom. 13.1.2.</hi> Yet I cannot but put the Lords on earth in mind, how the ſame Apoſtle ſaith in the ſame place, that Rulers ought not to be a terrour to good works, but to the evil. But while oppreſſion and injuſtice in any, is either connived at, or paſt by upon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint unpuniſhed, the wicked growe bold by their impunity, and the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy becomes a terrour, and the Law no other then a ſnare to all honeſt men.</p>
               <p>My Requeſt to you now, is neither for place nor promotion, though theſe be due to deſerving men, as the rewards of vertue.</p>
               <p>Therefore I ſhall never envy nor upbrayde any upon whom the ſame are conferred by a State, or other; but give me leave to tell you, while the poor are neglected, the oppreſſed unrelieved, and juſtice not done freely in your gates, that is, openly and not in Chambers, ſecurity or comfort you cannot long have in the enjoyment of them.</p>
               <p>I have wearied and waſted my ſelf ever ſince the Parl: firſt ſate down, in ſeeking to remove oppreſſors from their Seats, and gaining juſtice for poor people, but never to this preſent day could I bring my purpoſe to paſſe; for which I blame not the Parliament, but ſuch as ſit there in right of our Countrey, who only mind themſelves, and do their own work, regardleſs of us and our Countrey.</p>
               <p>For by fitting there, they become great, purchaſers of Lands and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, fare <hi>Dives</hi> like, while we at home are ſpoiled of all, and here diſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regarded <hi>Lazarous-like,</hi> lies at their doors begging for juſtice, but never yet could taſte the leaſt of their Crums, ſo as from them I am hopeleſs ever to obtain any good.</p>
               <p>If I had been a Solicitor or Agent for Cavaliers at <hi>Goldſmiths-Hall,</hi> to the Committee of Sequeſtrations, or to the Parliament, I might have got Wealth, and had the countenance of the great ones, and found ready diſpatch of buſineſs. I know one poor Solicitor that way hath gained <hi>2.</hi> or <hi>3000</hi> l. at the leaſt.</p>
               <p>But I agitating for a poor plundered People, could never gain the favour as the reading of a Petition.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> hath had poor Widow <hi>Blaythwaits</hi> Petition (one whom you ſometimes owned, and did good to) in his hand near <hi>3.</hi> years, yet could never find opportunity to preſent it, he held me in hand more then a year, he would preſent mine, and Captain <hi>Crakanthorps</hi> Petition; but in the cloſe, finding no real dealing with him, glad I was to take it from him, by no hand could I get acceſs unto juſtice.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:117774:25"/>
               <p>When I came the other day to preſent my Petition to the Councel of State, I deſired<note n="*" place="margin">A Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cel of State.</note> Mr. <hi>Scot</hi> to bring it in before you, he told me it was not proper for you, before he read or knew the Contents of it. If I had told him ſome prety ſtory of ſome hidden treaſure, I ſhould then have had ready admittance, and well rewarded; but while he Dog-like ſnatcht at the ſhadow, he loſt the Gold in his hand. Let all ſuch covetous wretches be ſo ſerved: <hi>I</hi> forbear to particularize, it is a ſtory fitter for <hi>Paſquile</hi> or <hi>Tarleton</hi> then your gravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               <p>I remember when the Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> came firſt Preſident to <hi>York,</hi> and for ſundry years after, the ſame being the uſual Cuſtome of the Kings learned Councel there, every day after dinner, for an houre and a half be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he went to Court, or entered upon any other buſineſs of ſtate, ſuiters by turns were called in, <hi>&amp;</hi> their Petitions read, being before received from them of courſe by the Clarke of the Petitions, there being two that attended eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry other week for that purpoſe, who had their diet, and a conſtant ſalary; for that purpoſe, ſo as the reference and attendance to the ſuitors was no way chargeable, none being neceſſitated to wait for anſwer longer then two days at the moſt, a good preſident for you and the Councel of State to follow.</p>
               <p>By which doings, for ſundry years, he kept the North free from oppreſſions, and mightily gained upon the affections of the people.</p>
               <p>The which when he gave over, and begun to be proud, and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, his Table became a ſnare to him, and his glory departed, and ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter followed the down-fall of him, and that Court; and how he was after proſecuted with the envy of the people, his tryal and death is enough to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon his tryal I was by the Lord <hi>Whitlock</hi> brought before the Lords in Parliament, and preſented to them, as a ruinated Gentleman by him: with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out me, it was then ſaid, they could not have made forth any conſiderable thing againſt him, of his illegal, regal actings in the North: then I had the plaudite and thanks, not only of that Committee, but of many other emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Members of the Houſe with many and large, (though then undeſired,) promiſes to procure me juſtice, and do great matters; for which ſervice I was committed by Juſtice <hi>Dikes,</hi> (one of the Deputies Creatures) to <hi>Carlile Caſtle;</hi> upon my return home, after my attendance upon the Tryal upon my own charge, but <hi>John Musgrave</hi> was never after owned.</p>
               <p>My proſecuting againſt our Malignant Committees, though I got a priſon: yet you gained both honour and friends thereby.</p>
               <p>Vpon your encouragement, I brought a liſt of the concealed Delinquents
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:117774:25"/>of our Countrey, and proved the ſame before the Committee of Lords and Commons for Sequeſtrations, which coſt me in attendance near <hi>100</hi> l. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn you again your Order.</p>
               <p>I hope you will ſo order the buſineſs, for if you pleaſe I know you can do it, that <hi>I</hi> may have ſome proportionable ſatisfaction for my former ſervice, loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and ſufferings, and ſome right done to my ſuffering friends.</p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Wilfrid Lawſon,</hi> for his pretended loſſes by <hi>Hambelton,</hi> without either Law or Act, Order, or Ordinance of Parliament, could raiſe <hi>3000</hi> l. for his loſſes from the poor Countrey, that never did him wrong, the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey being then delivered up to <hi>Hambleton</hi> by the Cowardiſe and treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Lawſon,</hi> and his Confederates there.</p>
               <p>But the poor Widow <hi>Blaithwait</hi> cannot be heard, <hi>I</hi> deſire you to peruſe Mr. <hi>Worſley,</hi> and my poor Mothers Petitions, with others I ſent you, that I may obtain ſo much favour, as to procure us common right, I may be thought in remembring my former actings, to hunt after praiſe or reward; truly I had been altogether ſilent, even as I was in my former troubles in the Fleet, and buried the ſame in oblivion, if I and my ſuffering friends of the North, for whom I agitate, had receeived any common right or juſtice from the Parliament, which if you procure us, we ſhall with all thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs acknowledge the ſame; and you will obliege me to be ever, as truly I am,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Lordſhips humble Servant. JOHN M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SGRAVE.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>21. June, 1649.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <trailer>For the Right Honourable, <hi>John Bradſhaw,</hi> Lord Preſident of the Councel of State, ſitting at <hi>White-Hall.</hi>
               </trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:117774:26"/>
               <argument>
                  <p>Here I though good to inſert a letter written to Sr. <hi>Thomas VVitherington,</hi> formerly print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in regard it relates to our former and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent grievances.</p>
               </argument>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Expected ere this to have heard of your report to have been made to the Houſe, upon the vote paſſed for <hi>M. Cracanthorp</hi> and my ſelf, for the great loſſes that we have ſuſtained by the Enemy, the Iuſtices of the peace, and Com. of <hi>Array</hi> in <hi>Cumberland</hi> and <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merland;</hi> I here attended the laſt winter, 13. weeks before I could get the Petition preſented to the Houſe, ſix moneths upon the Committee I waited before I could get any vote paſſed upon the Petition, ſince the vote of the Committee was made, which you are to report unto the Houſe, it is now nigh four moneths; yet nothing done, which makes me much fear that little good is intended us, and that we ſhall be made more miſerable in ſeeking the recovery of what we have loſt, then in loſing the ſame, undergo more hardſhip, and be brought to greater ſtraits by waiting on you, then by lying in the Enemies priſons for you. You know the deferring of Iuſtice; in Law is holden for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyal of Iuſtice. The Parliament put us to an oath to maintain the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full liberty of the Subject; the Enemy becauſe I would not joyn with them in the breach of it, and in betraying my Country, forced me into <hi>Exile,</hi> and ſeized on that little Eſtate I had; now again upon the report of <hi>M. Liſle</hi> (after his many differings and puttings off, even to the hazard of the loſſe of our Countrey, and if Sir <hi>John Brown</hi> (as is well known) with his Scottiſh forces (upon <hi>Cumberland</hi> forces deſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him) by his valour had not prevented it, the Enemy by ſome of our ſeeming friends who joyned with them, had without any great difficulty, no oppoſition being made by Col. <hi>Lawſon,</hi> effected their deſigns in that Country.) Of my pretended refuſal to anſwer, which I did not, but onely deſired the Interrogatories to adviſe of, before I anſwered for matter of Law, which contrary to Law he reſuſed to grant me, though earneſtly deſired, all which may fully appear by my
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:117774:26"/>anſwer and reaſons given for not anſwering then to the Interrogato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries before the Committee, (and taken in writing by <hi>M. Liſle</hi> himſelf, before the ſame Committee and ſome other members of the Houſe, and which was then read unto me) am I again caſt into priſon, and condemned thereunto unheard, and my greateſt fault (if any be) in this caſe, is my Lawfull maintenance of our common freedoms, and my doubting, and deſire to be reſolved before I ſhould act that, which ſeemed to me then, and now I know to be not agreeable to Law; and here I lie in priſon for this, while Traitors and the grand Enemies to the State, are by this means ſuffered to walk <hi>London</hi> ſtreets, even they of whom I complain; for which I cannot but blame <hi>M. Liſle,</hi> being thus injured by him, and my Countrey almoſt undone; For as S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Cook</hi> well obſerveth, it is the greateſt Injuſtice, when the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent is oppreſſed under colour of Juſtice; whereby we ought to be protected: I am perſwaded that if that Honourable Houſe by whom I was committed were truly acquainted with my ſuffering condition, and knew the ground thereof, they would not ſuffer me to lie in priſon one day longer; and if they rightly underſtood the unſetled ſtate of our Countrey, and what harm the neglect thereof hath been to both Kingdoms (this and <hi>Scotland</hi>) and what advantage to the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and alſo what further evil may enſue thereupon; I believe we had not been ſo ſlighted as we have been, neither our Countrey men have had ſuch juſt cauſe to have complained of delay and neglect, as they by their letters to me ſent daily do, neither had the adverſary I ſuppoſe, been ſo born out.</p>
               <p>As long as honeſt men are thus ſlighted, neglected, and kept under, their juſt complaints thus delayed and ſuppreſſed, while Traitors. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, and Delinquents be thus countenanced and protected, as thoſe of whom we complain have been and ſtill are; while the greateſt places of truſt and command are conferred on, and continued in the hands of Traitors, and the grand Enemies of the State, as hath been, and now is with us, and ſtill they are kept up in their Authorities; while the Parliaments and the Kingdoms faithfull friends and ſervants are thus moleſted, oppreſſed, and ſhut up in priſons for their good af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, forwardneſſe, and willingneſſe to ſerve the State and their Countrey: How can we expect the reſtauration of our ancient and long loſt Liberties? How can we look for an end of theſe our trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles? While things are thus carried on, little peace can be hoped for
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:117774:27"/>this poor and diſtreſſed Kingdom. Let us no more cheriſh the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent in our boſom, which having got ſtrength will again wound us, if not deſtroy us: I could wiſh that theſe troublers and Enemies of our State, againſt whom onely I inform, and with whom I onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, may no longer be ſuffered to eſcape, but may be brought to condigne puniſhment, according to the Law, and merit of their offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, leſt by others faults the Parliament ſhould ſuffer in their credit, leſt that it ſhould be thought the Parliament were offended with as for ſeeking Juſtice, and preſſing forward our Countries juſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints and grievances, leſt it ſhould be thought the Parliament ſhould ſeem to juſtifie (or connive) at theſe their lawleſſe practiſes and oppreſsions (which we are ready in a legal way to make good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our charge) by forbearance and ſufferance of them: For it is a maxime in Law, <hi>Qui non prohibet quod prohibere poteſt, aſſentiri vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detur;</hi> [He that ſuffereth not that which he may let, is conceived and ſaid in Law to aſſent.] Let no ſuch blot lie upon that Honourable Houſe; let not the potency of our adverſaries overthrow the juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our cauſe, neglect us no more, leſt (beſides the blame and out-cries for Juſtice) you bring ruin upon us and your ſelves, by lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us open to the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> which may the ſooner invite <hi>Ormond</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade us with his Popiſh and revolted Forces, having ſuch an eaſie en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance, if the ſame be not prevented.</p>
               <p>As you tender the good and quiet of the State, timely provide for this, and have reſpect to our poor Countrey; let all Delinquents, Traitors, and men diſ-affected, all ſuch as are tainted with covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or cowardize, be removed out of all Authorities, and the ſame put in the hands of confiding men, fearing God, and hating covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and all baſeneſſe; ſuch as would not be in the worſt of times car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away, or corrupted through fear, or loſſe of goods, or hope of preferment, to joyn with, or ſubmit unto the Enemy, or act in a neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trality, which is holden for moſt deteſtable: Neglect of thoſe parts may prove of dangerous conſequence; There, and not well elſe-where in the North, may the <hi>Iriſh</hi> land at their pleaſure, and daily are expected there; from thence <hi>Digby</hi> by connivance of ſome of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders there, (as is conceived) had free and ready paſſage into the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Man,</hi> and ſo for <hi>Ireland;</hi> from thence the Earl of <hi>Antrum</hi> had like paſſage, and way into <hi>Ireland,</hi> with the Royal Commiſsions for Ceſſation of Arms there, which produced ſuch ſad effects in that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:117774:27"/>Kingdom. <hi>Montroſſe</hi> made his way for <hi>Scotland</hi> twice that way, to the great loſſe of that Kingdom, he invaded <hi>Scotland</hi> and took <hi>Dumfrece,</hi> hence the Earl of <hi>New-Caſtle</hi> had his firſt riſe of his Popiſh Army in the North, and daily ſupplies of men and monies, till the reduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof by the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Horſe; hence ſince the reducement the Enemy in <hi>Dublin</hi> and the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Man</hi> had Cole and Victuals: Here the whole Gentry are Malignants, Delinquents, Papiſts, Popiſh, or baſe Temporizers; Here not ten of the Gentry in both theſe Counties, nay, I dare ſay, not ſo many have proved Cordial to the State, but have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted themſelves, or acted to and with the Enemy; Here the Gentry have revolted ſince the reducement thereof, more then once or twice. Here Will, and Oppreſsion, reigns more then in any Countrey now ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to the State, ſo long as the powers and Authorities reſide in the hands of ſuch Neutrals, Temporizers, Self-ſeekers, Traitors and Delinquents, as now it is, the Enemy (though peace for the preſent were concluded and ſetled) yet might upon new and after diſcontents of a ſudden, endanger the loſſe of the whole North, by the help of that Popiſh faction in thoſe parts, who have got in their hands the chief places of truſt and Command there, though you had no care nor regard of us, yet for your own good, prevent this miſchief, the which done may produce (though little conſidered) the fruit which may prove to be a well grounded peace to the whole Kingdom; Though neglect of us, could be no prejudice to the publick, which will be of no ſmall concernment (as I have already ſhown) yet the redreſſe of our Countries grievances in common equity ought not to be ſo light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſſed over, all which hitherto (but all in vain, for fourteen moneths together) have been preſſed on, but by one Committee or other ſtill fruſtrated; and in Juſtice you cannot deny us audience, and an equal trial either at the Common-law, or in full Parliament, as in your wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms ſhall ſeem beſt for the publick, and our particular good, for that the Law is our common birthright; which we may without offence (I hope) and do challenge and claim the benefit thereof, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we have no cauſe to doubt or be fearfull in putting our ſelves forth, conſidering how that general rule in Law is ſtill in force: <hi>Quod curia regis non debeat deficere conquerentibus in Juſtitia adhibenda; That the Kings Court ſhould never be failing (to ſuch as complain) in the doing of Juſtice.</hi> And of Courts Judicial, we acknowledge the Parliament Supream, which ever hath been, and I hope ſtill will be the great and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:117774:28"/>faith full up-holder of the Common-Law, and of the rights and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of all the loyal and true-hearted Free-born of the Kingdom; I pray you, good Sir, peruſe theſe papers and Copies of Letters, the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginals I have all, except two, which Maſter <hi>Blaxſton</hi> hath, to whom they were ſent and delivered; withall, I would intreat you to preſent this my Petition to the Houſe of Commons, <hi>M. Speaker</hi> hath ſeen it, and ſaith he will ſpeak to it; I could not preſſe him further, in reſpect he had formerly preſented one for me: which was referred to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Committee, but by <hi>M. Liſle</hi> (who is the Chair-man) ſuppreſſed; and I could never hear more of it; the ground of this my Petition, I hope you will let me underſtand what you will do here concerning the whole matter, by this bearer Maſter <hi>Hobkins</hi> (the Warden of the <hi>Fleet</hi>) which hath ſhown me kindneſſe, in his readineſſe to do me this favour, if by your means and the Juſtice of the houſe I may obtain my liberty, and our Countries cauſe put in a way of trial without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther procraſtination, I ſhall not be unthankfull, but ever reſt</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>From the Fleet priſon</hi> 
                     <date>this 25. <hi>of the</hi> 12. <hi>Moneth,</hi> 1645.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Yours to ſerve and honour you, JOHN MUSGRAVE.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:117774:28"/>
            <head>POST-SCRIPT.</head>
            <p>I Omitted to ſet forth, how Sir <hi>Arthur Hazlerig</hi> within theſe <hi>2.</hi> or <hi>3.</hi> years, and ſince he became ruler of the North, hath got an Eſtate in Lands there, worth eight or ten thouſand pounds <hi>per Annum,</hi> part by oppreſſion; but the moſt of it by buying the <hi>Common-wealths</hi> Lands at far undervalues; the Surveyors being ſuch, who durſt not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe him, but made returns of the values as he deſired, which if reviewed, will appear to be true: His Man <hi>Pearſon,</hi> who the other day was worth little or nothing when his Maſter came to <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> hath purchaſed as much Lands very near as his Maſter was worth when the Wars began: <hi>Fitch</hi> the Governour of <hi>Carlile</hi> under him, hath likewiſe infinitely inriched himſelf by overburdening the Countrey with free quarter, and exceſſive Taxes and Leavies of Corn and money, which he hath never accompted for, notwithſtanding he hath received conſtant pay from the State for that Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon; not a people in <hi>England</hi> ſo oppreſſed as we, yet never to this day could procure any that ſit in Parl: in the right of our Countrey, to preſent a Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for us, which is the very cauſe I have thus ſet my ſelf forth, having ſpent that little the Enemy hath left me in a fruitleſs attendance: All which I humbly ſubmit to the grave conſideration of the Councel of State, begging their helping hand and liberty to prove what I here aſſert, before they judge it ſcandals, as ſome have ſaid it to be.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JOHN MUSGRVE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="erratum">
            <p>
               <hi>Reader I pray amend the faults of the</hi> Printer <hi>with thy Pen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
